Come to talk to you about the latest academic research and scientific development
來跟大家談最新的學術研究跟科學發展
Today I am very happy and honored to invite a researcher from the China Wen Zhe Institute of our school
今天我很高興也很榮幸邀請到本院中國溫哲研究所的研究員
Come to talk with you about China's first vernacular Bible
與士學教授來跟大家談中國第一部白話文聖經
From the seventh ninth year to the eighth year
第七九年到第八年吧
Dr. Lee is a Master of English Literature from Commonwealth University
李博士是普人大學英文文學碩士
PhD in Comparative Literature, University of Skagow
斯加哥大學比較文學博士
Establishment Day Education Department of English, Soochow University Institute of Comparative Literature, Pujin University
成立日教育東吳大學英文系普人大學比較文學研究所
National Shiwan University English Institute and Translation Institute
國立四萬大學英文研究所及翻譯研究所
He is now a researcher at the Institute of Philosophy
他現在是本院文哲所的研究員
He is also a Professor of Peace at the Translation Institute of Normal University
也是師大翻譯研究所和平教授
and agricultural researcher at the Translation Center of the Chinese University of Hong Kong
以及香港中文大學翻譯中心的農務研究員
He is more familiar with engineering than Professor
比教授工學很熟
so i shouldn't have read this
所以我本來不應該念這個
However, Professor Li has won many farmer awards including young assistants from our hospital.
但是李教授曾經得過很多農民包括本院的年輕助作獎
Soochow University Outstanding Campus Tour Award
東吳大學傑出校遊獎
He just heard that he also gave lectures when he was competing for general universities and book schools
他才聽說,他在競爭普人大學及書校也有講的時候
I lost to Cai Yinglin, so there is nothing wrong with this
輸給了蔡英霖,所以這個情有可言
In 2010 and 2011, all translation research papers commemorative awards were sent
2010及2011年送齊翻譯研究論文紀念獎
and National Science Council and Book Research Award, etc.
以及國科會及書研究獎等
Well, Professor Aristotle's education is rich
那麼阿里士學教授的學養豐富
Know six or seven languages
語言懂六七種
Then the writing waits for students
那麼著作等生
Well, his works include Chinese and Western Civilization English People
那麼他的著作包括中西民學英語人
Late Ming Dynasty in China to Middle Ages in Europe
中國晚明以歐洲中世紀
Qingming Jesuit Western Classical Administrative Road Story Exam
明朗耶穌會西洋古典行政道故事考試
Mingming Jesuits Translating Literature and Other Books
明朗耶穌會翻譯文學論等書
And he has translated a lot of books, I want to say that I don't mean to read them here
而且他翻譯過很多的書,我想說我不意義在這裡念
But I recently saw a comment
不過我最近看到一個評論
I said, I can't see it, I just can see it
我說,看不到我剛好看得到
Then this comment thinks that he is the one who studies the translated literature of the late Ming Dynasty all over the world.
那麼這個評論認為他是全世界研究晚明的翻譯文學
first person, then i'll paraphrase here
第一人,那麼我就在這裡轉述
But he didn't get a chance to read this comment
但是他沒有機會看這個評論
So it can be seen that his translation in the late Ming Dynasty
那麼可見他在這個晚明的翻譯
So because the book will matter, this translation
所以是因為書會事,這個翻譯
This history has a very important and authoritative position
這段歷史有很重要的很權威的地位
do a lot of work on this
在這方面做很多的工作
including very detailed
包括非常詳盡的
Restrain this late Ming game-like translation of the classic
抑制這個晚明的遊戲樣翻譯的經典
Although I still have to speak publicly
雖然我還是要公開講
I advised him not to live so carefully
我勸他不必這麼仔細的住
I've been told this by him
這我已經大被跟他講過
But these jobs are very big jobs
不過這些工作都是非常大的工作
and it takes time
而且要耗費的時間
This is the case in all aspects of knowledge and physical strength
學問、體力各方面都是這個
Unprecedented 8 project investment
前所未有的8工程投資
We also hope he gets these things done soon
我們也希望他很快把這些東西完成
Professor of Governance also served as Telephone Newspaper
理事學教授也曾經擔任電話報
"China Times"
《中國時報》
The Sino-British Daily has only Times columns and Su Ping writers
《中英日報》只有時報的專欄跟蘇平作家
So I guess his name is familiar to you all
所以我想他的名字各位並不陌生
Although you still have to ask me at noon today
雖然今天中午還要來問我
Should I Study Liliology or Lishuangxue?
到底該念理事學還是理爽學
we are the word is very old
我們是這個字很古老
The word "Military" in the above book is the word
上書裡面的軍事就是這個字
so this
所以這個
Today's speech is actually
今天演講事實上是
You said it was mentioned in a small talk with me once
你叫說有一次跟我在閒談中談到的
I think this topic is very suitable
我覺得這個題目很適合
I didn't expect to arrange the left arrangement and the right arrangement
沒想到左安排右安排
It's a coincidence that it's scheduled for Christmas today.
居然很巧合就安排在今天聖誕節
this is totally unexpected
這個完全出乎意料
Because the small root of knowledge is Tuesday
因為知識小根就是禮拜二
so tuesday
所以禮禮拜二
Christmas
聖誕節
Attach your first "Vernacular Bible"
附上你的第一本《白話文聖經》
it's a match made in heaven
這是天作之合
We also give a big round of applause to welcome everyone
我們也非常掌聲歡迎大家
Thank you Vice President Wang today
今天謝謝王副院長
I don't want to be sorry today
我今天不要抱歉一點
I compare why
我比較為什麼
I usually feel like I have a cold
我平時覺得我感冒
But it's stupid to talk about it
可是卻居然在講很傻呀
started yesterday
昨天開始的
Before I ask you, I figured it out myself
問你前面我自己都搞得我拉清楚
but say so
不過這樣講
He might be more magnetic
他可能比較有磁性一點
I have a self-deprecating place
我有一顆自嘲的地方
what i'm going to talk about today
那我今天要談的這個
After the first "Vernacular Bible"
經過第一部《白話文聖經》
Is a Chinese Jesuit
是一個華國耶穌會士
He Qingtai
叫賀清泰
OK He Jintao said he translated it
OK 何錦濤這個他說 他是翻譯的
this is a very interesting person
這是一個非常有趣的人
I'll talk more about him later
待會兒我會詳細再談他
before talking about him i think
在談他之前 我想
The first of our Academia Sinica to come to Taiwan
我們中央研究院來臺灣的第一位
The first dean, Mr. Hu Shizhi
第一任的這個院長 胡世之先生
start from the beginning
從一開始開始談起
OK Hu Shiyou is very respectful
OK 胡世有非常崇派
At this time, this person who can step into the academic hall
這時候這個能夠踏進學術的殿堂
Actually, I think personally
實際上是我覺得就我個人來講
The key is the influence of Hu Shi OK
關鍵是胡世的這個影響 OK
this Hushi
這個胡世
I probably read Hu Shi's book when I was in high school
胡世這一本書我大概在高中的時候就已經讀過了
One of the things Hu Shi said in your book
你們這本書裡面胡世說的一個
recent in 50 years
最近在50年
But it is spoken in English
但是它那個是英文講的話
OK
OK
So life in English is pushed back 50 years
所以那從英文生命在往前推50年
The vernacular novel of this life is
那這個生命的白話小說是
Vernacular literature in the past 1000 years
人就於1000年來的白話文學
has the same big drawback
有同樣的一個大缺點
That is to say, the adoption of vernacular
也就是說白話的採用
still meaningless
仍就是無意義的
meaningful
所意義的
doesn't make sense
並不是有意義的
in other words
換句話說
if no english is spoken
如果沒有英文講的話
this story thinks before it
這個故事認為在它之前
This use of vernacular
白話文的這個使用
So
那麼
is a
是一種
How to say
怎麼說
If it is not a product of the bookstore
如果不是書場的產物的話
then it is
那麼就是
Chat until there is no Jinshi
聊到沒有口上進士
or those who raise people
或是舉人的那些
the literati
聊到的這個文人
Then pick up the pen
然後就筆約拿起來
Initiate old income
發起老收
write a novel
寫小說來了
OK
OK
this
這個
so is a
所以是一種
unconsciously
unconsciously
written in vernacular here
在這個用白話來寫
writing
寫作
Hu Shi is greater than consciousness, probably like this
胡適大於意識大概是這樣子
so for him
所以對他來講
these people
這些人
write this vernacular
寫這個白話文
neither
都不是
conclusively in writing
conclusively在寫的
ok
ok
not conscious
不是自覺性說
I want to create in vernacular
我要用白話文來創作
or to write
或者說來寫作
this
這個
i miss him
我想他
he thought before
他認為以前
people are not like this
人都不是這個樣子
but i personally
但我個人
before
以前
did not touch this
沒有接觸這個
Mingjing
明經之際
Before this work of the Society of Jesus
耶穌會的這個作作之前
What is Hu Shi talking about?
胡適講什麼東西
because he asks him again
因為他問重來他
I just want to ask him something
我就想問他什麼東西
Later I realized that
後來我就發覺說
Hu Shi said this
胡適講這個話
seems a little too much
似乎稍微有點過分的一點
a little too fast
太急了一點
ok
ok
So I personally at this point in time
所以我個人這個時間點上
There are many things that are not necessarily their own
有很多不一定自己的東西
In fact, not yet
其實實際上是都還沒有
no one has seen it in a
還沒有人在一個看到過
OK
OK
so
所以
This is also extenuating
這也是前有可原的啦
OK
OK
The one about He Qiantai that I want to talk about today
我今天要講的這一個賀千泰的
old and new bible
古新聖經
not such a book
就不是這樣子的一本
so-called unintentional
所謂無意的
So-called
所謂的
this translated bible
這個翻譯出來的一部聖經
but
而是
Intentional
有意的
use vernacular
要用白話文
to translate the bible
來翻譯聖經的
And this vernacular
而且這個白話文
i don't know use this baby
我不知道用這個寶寶
Although He Qiantai lives in Beijing
雖然賀千泰住在這個北京
OK
OK
he is
他是
he is the jesuit history of france
他是法國的耶穌會史
but
不過
he arrived when he was very young
他很小的時候就到
this one
這一個
Centaur
人馬
OK
OK
so he
所以他
he calls himself this
他自稱的這個
Italian
義大利文
is better than his this
是比他的這個
How to say
怎麼說
here in french
法文這個來
much better
好得很多啦
OK
OK
When he came to China
當他來到中國之後
he put this
他就把這個
when he was first
他最早的時候
actually
其實
because we need to know something
因為我們要知道一點
this china
這個中國
in the qing dynasty
在清朝的時候
Mandarin
國語
not us today
並不是我們今天
the so-called national language
講的這個所謂國語
ok or the so-called Beijing dialect in mainland China
ok 或者是大陸所謂的北京話
The national language of the Qing Dynasty was Manchu
清朝的國語是滿文
ok is manchu
ok 是滿文
When you come to China
那來到中國的時候
his first
他這個第一個
What about translating the above attempts
翻譯上面的嘗試呢
That's Manchu
那就是滿文
this attempt of the bible
聖經的這個嘗試
Then wait until he finishes the Manchu Bible
那等下滿文聖經他做完了之後
he just started
他才開始
The nerve to do Chinese
做中文的這個神經
ok
ok
The Chinese nerve
這個中文的神經
I don't think it's a
我不大認為說它是一種
How to say
怎麼說
commonly known as
一般人都稱之為
Beijing Guanhua
北京觀化
ok a language like this
ok 這樣子的一種語言
i am not a linguist
我不是一個語言學家
But I always feel that visualization is a class language
但是我總覺得觀化是一種階級性的語言
OK
OK
The one that talks about visualization
講觀化的這一個
you sooner or later
你在遲早方面
You are even in the aspect of intonation
你甚至在intonation這方面
I'm afraid it's all
恐怕都是
must have that
必須要有那種
this kind of knowledge
知識的這一種
a certain level of knowledge
某種知識層面的這一個人
then he will speak
那麼他才會講
OK
OK
Then even if you live in Beijing
那你即使居住在北京的話
You may not be talking about this so-called visualization
你講的也未必是這一個所謂的觀化
but he was writing
而是老死他在寫
For example, when writing this Le Tuo box
比方說寫這個樂陀箱子的時候
The so-called Beijing Tuyu
所謂的這一個北京圖語
OK
OK
Graphics are a little harder to hear
圖語比較難聽一點
Let's speak Beijing Shuyu
我們就說北京書語吧
OK
OK
The Beijing Shuyu written by He Jinla
那賀金拉的這北京書語
when he writes well
他寫得好的時候
really great
的確是非常棒的
OK
OK
let's see the next one
我們看下一張
Let me check this one from He Jinla first.
這個我先查一下這顆賀金拉的這一個
this person is good
這一個人好
This He Jinla's
這顆賀金拉的
It is now China from 1770
現在是1770年來中國的
its actually a generation of jesuits
它實際上是一代耶穌會士
The end of the article is in Xinrong because
文末在新榮是因為
Its point in time is already
它的時間點已經是
to this former farmer
到了這個前農
If you count the first generation of Jesuits
如果說要算第一代耶穌會士的話
That should be counted immediately
那應該是要有立馬都這個算起的
That was around 1588, 283
那是1588、283年左右的這個時間
Feature Master 1770's
特性大師1770年來的
It's hundreds of years away from this
跟這個立馬都已經相差了好幾百年了
ok
ok
so in the middle
所以這中間
In fact, China has gone through that kind of
這中間其實中國是經過那種
religious tolerance
對寬容宗教
Then next to bondage religion
然後接下來束縛宗教
ok
ok
Then just ban you Catholic
接下來乾脆就禁止你這個天主教
this one goes into china
這一個進入中國
ok
ok
that but
那但是
Although it says access to prohibit this
雖然說進入禁止這個
Off home is forbidden
關家是禁止
Catholicism enters China
天主教進入中國
But the Catholic Church is telling the truth
可是天主教說實在的
did not die
並沒有死掉
He became an underground frontrunner
他變成地下的前流
He's very active underground
他在地下活躍得非常厲害
Thousand yuan is to drive out some missionaries
千元是把一些傳教士都已經趕出去了
but then again
但是話說回來
If your calendar is very good
如果你歷算非常好
very good at math
數學非常好
very good legislation
立法非常好
astronomy is very good
天文學非常好
Shenzhen understands painting
深圳領會畫畫
Even if these people are the most severe warriors
這些人即使是進教最嚴厲的勇證
He also let them stay in this coffin
他也讓他們留在這個棺林裡面
So in the coffin forest
所以棺林裡面
I raised a group of so-called generals from the West
就養了一群西方的所謂將器
or painter
或是畫師
you drink brilliantly
你喝精采
when you come to china
來中國的時候
He probably never thought that he would be a flower stand
他大概沒有想到說他會去當這一個花架
just because he's a little
只是因為他有一點那麼
this talent in painting
繪畫上面的這一個天分
OK not a little big
OK不是一點很大
talent for painting
繪畫上面天分
So when he arrived in Beijing, people asked him what he was doing
所以當他這個到到北京的時候人家問他說您做什麼事情
He made this one Latin very well
他出了這一個拉丁文非常好
OK
OK
Then China with this one
那麼中國跟這一個
There is often that kind of border diplomacy with Russia
跟俄國之間常常有那種邊境外交上面的
trade or
貿易或者說
Even the question of national borders
甚至國界的這個問題
So he often intervenes in this Secondary School
所以他常常介入這個中二
this
這個
trade or
貿易或者說
some political issues
政治上面的一些問題
translated a lot of this
翻譯了很多這個
something specialized becomes latin
專門的東西成為拉丁文
show this two
給這個二方看
OK
OK
Of course I don't know how his biography is.
我當然是不知道他二文怎麼樣
but
但是
once wanted to join
有一次是想要加入
Russian Jesuits
俄國的耶穌會的
OK
OK
that anyway
那anyway
let's answer him
我們再回答他
His identity as a chemist
他化家的身份
He is the descendant of the so-called Hercynian faction
他是所謂千公里面海西派的傳人
a hercynian is actually a
海西派實際上是一個
Haixi is from the west
海西就是西方來的嘛
The west of the sea is here
海的西方來了嘛
In fact, it was Wolf Shilin who shouted it out.
實際上是狼式林他們喊出來的
Or because of Wolf Shilin when they were talking
或是說因為狼式林他們在會話的時候
The inscription is Hercynian wolf-style forest
對落款是海西狼式林
So there was such a so-called Hercynian
所以就出現了這麼一個所謂的海西派
He Jintai is the last member of this faction.
賀金太算是這一派的最後一個人了
When they came to China in 1776
1776年來華的時候
Wolf Forest has been lost for five years
狼式林已經失掉了五年
So He Jintai has never seen this wolf-style forest
所以賀金太是沒有見過這一個狼式林的
But He Jintai
但是賀金太
Earlier, Wang Licheng asked He Jintai and said
前面王立誠問問賀金太說
You go to imitate this wolf forest or something
你去模仿這一個狼式林的什麼什麼什麼之類的
include this one
包括這一個
Bai Juntu
白俊徒
Bai Juntu also sent
白俊徒也曾經派
make this
弄成這個
have voted
有票過
including Bai Juntu
包括白俊徒
He Juntu is more than you
赫俊徒還多你沒過
so
所以
He Juntu is thousands of kilometers away
赫俊徒在千公里面
calculate
算算
If you want to compare with Wang Shilin
你要跟王士林比起來的話
he's not first class
他不是第一流的
Huajia
海西派的華家
not much sister in law
不多的嫂嫂
also for this
也為這個
how do you say
一個怎麼說
one in court
公庭裡面的一個
Emphasis on location
所重視
one of Hu Jintao's
胡錦濤的一個人
he wrote a book called
他寫了一本書叫
Picture Record of the Imperial Court
國朝院畫錄
He Jintai
說這個賀錦太
Donglin Mao
東林茅
That is to say, he is good at drawing
也就是說他擅長畫
this painted bird
這個畫鳥
OK to draw a bird
OK畫鳥
what bird
什麼鳥呢
I didn't understand the nouns
本來用名詞我也看不懂
called Haiqing
叫海青
blue is the love of blue sky
青是青天的情
OK
OK
Later, the seascape paper used to look up the dictionary was old silver or something like that.
後來去查字典用的海景紙是老銀之類的
So I showed a picture of this one
所以我就秀了一張這一個
Lao Yin painted by He Jintai is over there
賀金台畫的老銀在那邊
Except for this old silver
除了這個老銀之外
He Jintai actually painted many other things
賀金台其實他也畫過很多其他的東西
In addition, I found another record of this painting by him.
另外又找到一張他畫的這個錄
we can see
我們可以看出來
In fact, in a certain sense of the Hercynian school
在海西派其實某一個意義上面
It is a combination of Chinese painting and Western painting
是結合中國繪畫跟西方繪畫在一起的
I am not an art history researcher
我不是一個藝術史的研究者
That's probably all we're talking about
我們講的大概就只是這樣子而已
I also know He Jin
我還知道賀金
did you say we must be free
你有沒有說我們一定有空到
Words from Gu Gong Museum Area
顧公博物院區的話
Mr. Gu's office and Father Wu
顧公室還有武父
Our Taipei Gugong
我們臺北顧公
I don't know Mr. Gu in mainland China
大陸的顧公我不清楚
He has a martial father to Mr. Gu
他對顧公有武父
This painting by He Jintai
賀金台的這一個畫
So He Jintai
所以賀金台
as the artist
是以這個畫師的身份
In the Qing Palace, the interaction with the emperor is relatively large
在清宮裡面跟皇帝互動比較大的
OK
OK
that in private
那私底下
sorry
對不起
Another concern is the translation
另外一個關注就是翻譯
during diplomatic translation
外交翻譯時
he is always doing one thing
他常常在做一件事情
OK
OK
private translation
私底下的翻譯
Of course it's to fuck them
那當然就是搞他們
sorry
對不起
do their own bible translations
做他們自己的聖經的翻譯工作
i just said
我剛剛已經說過了
This Manchu is the national language of the Qing Dynasty
這個滿文是清代的國語
so
所以
this He Jintai
這個賀金泰
Of course it's drawn from 1770
當然是從1770年來畫
After painting in 1770
1770年來畫之後
he started this bible
他開始做的這個聖經
you can change it
你可以換一下
That's not it
不是這個
no
不是
There is a Date
有個Date
Ok,Date
Ok,Date
Ok
Ok
he probably
他大概
Come to China in 1770 I think
1770年來華我想
He has to learn Manchu
他還得學滿文
Ok, so it's probably impossible to say
Ok,所以大概不可能就是說
Since 1770
1770年就開始
This translation, this Manchu Bible
這個翻譯,這個滿文聖經
Ok
Ok
but for some
但是對於一些
words spoken by a language genius
語言天才來講的話
I think
我想
Well
呃
It is also difficult for us to say that he cannot be within three to five years
我們也很難說他不能在三五年之內
uh at least after some degree of this manchu
呃至少經過某種程度的這個滿文
Manchu in all aspects should be a kind of
各方面滿文應該是一種
flat phonetic characters, i don't understand
平音文字,我不懂
Ok, but I just because he should be a
Ok,但是我只要因為他應該是一種
Plain letters
平音文字
So under this Chinese
所以在這種中文下面
Well
呃
This country and scriptures from flat-yin script
來自平音文字的這個國度和經來
probably for Manchu
大概對於滿文
should be
應該是
It is also easier to enter the situation
還比較容易進入狀況的
OK
OK
so
所以
this
這個
when did he start translating manchu
他什麼時候開始翻譯滿文
We don't know about the bible
聖經這個我們是不知道的
so full bible
這麼滿文聖經
manuscript now
現在手稿
not herbal
不是草本
manuscript
手稿
It's in Japan's Toyo Bunko
是放在日本的東洋文庫的
I don't know why and where I went
我也不知道為什麼跑到哪邊去
OK
OK
Then the Japanese Toyo Bunko
那麼日本東洋文庫那邊
The title given is called
給的題目是叫做
Manchu complex
滿文復族
new covenant victory book
新就約勝書
I want to say that you will not belong to He Jintao
我想說你這不會是賀錦帶的
his title
他的title
OK
OK
I don't know what happened to his title
他的title是怎麼回事我不是很清楚
Completed this Manchu Bible in 1790
1790年完成這一個滿文聖經
This is certain because
這一點是可以確定的因為
He Jin has a friend
賀錦帶有一個朋友啊
This once wrote a letter saying
這個曾經寫了一封信說
In 1790, He Jindai completed the translation of the Manchu Bible
1790年賀錦帶完成滿文聖經的翻譯
OK
OK
so it's very, very clear
所以這一點是非常非常清楚的
You have to wait until the translation of the Manchu scriptures is finished
你要等到滿文生經翻譯完畢了
You put the most important thing in the Qing Dynasty
你把清朝最重要的這個
That is to say, the most important thing for Qing people is Manchu
就是說清人最重要是滿文
after you've done it
你把它做完了之後
You might just say come back
你才有可能就是說再回來
How do you say this
這個怎麼說
to deal with this
去應付這一
In fact, there are many more Han Chinese than Manchurians
其實比滿人還要多很多的這個漢人
OK
OK
so
所以
The earliest he could have been in the 1790s
他最快也應該是在1790年代
early 1790
1790年初
or 1790
或是1790年
He can start translating
他才有可能開始翻譯
this
這個
this nerve in Chinese
中文的這個神經
OK
OK
So
那麼
very interesting
很有趣的是
exist
在
This horse bean of the New Testament
新約的這個馬豆
Wanyue Green means Gospel
萬越綠是福音的意思
this
這個
this saint
這個聖徒
holy
聖
I don't think so
我想不用
i say
我都說
San Matthew
San Matthew
OK
OK
It is the Gospel of Madou
就是馬豆福音
When he was translating a gospel of horse beans
他翻譯著一種馬豆福音的時候
has a comment
有一條註解
write to say
寫到說
Dokei
道敬
this i think
這個我想
Impossible 1800 Daoist
不可能1800年道敬
this should be in the middle
這個應該中間
he is missing a word
他少了一個字
or super person this
或是超的人這個
one word missing
少了一個字
It should be one hundred and eighteen hundred years ago
應該是一百一千八百年前
Dokei
道敬
OK
OK
so
所以
this
這個
We can probably imagine that
我們大概可以想像就是說
this He Jintai
這個賀金泰
should be
應該是
in the 19th century
在19世紀
this one
這一個
that one
那一個
The moment the eighteenth turned to the nineteenth century
十八轉到19世紀的那一刻
OK
OK
he officially translated
他正式翻譯
this new music
這一個新音樂
OK
OK
what about old music
那舊音樂呢
I started translating a long time ago
老早就開始翻譯了
He flipped a lot of this old music
他翻了不少的這一個舊音樂
OK
OK
text also disappeared
文字也消失了
Well said
講得不錯
In total he actually translated
他總共其實翻譯了
If according to this Chinese volume
如果按照這個中文的這個卷
how to say this word
這個字的說法
He translated a total of 36 volumes
他總共翻譯了36卷
But what about the 36 volumes
但是這36卷呢
This roll cannot be brought
這個卷不能夠拿來跟
the book of the bible
聖經那一個卷字
Equal and close
等量而關
Because if the word in the Bible is written in English
因為聖經那一個卷字如果用英文的話
It's called Bokeh
是叫Bokeh
Libbe in Latin
拉丁文叫Libbe
so
所以
36 Chinese Rolls by He Jintao
赫金帶的36個中國卷
is equal to this western bible
是等於這個西方聖經的
About 56, 7 Bokeh
大概是56、7個Bokeh
ok
ok
this
這個
talking about being catholic
在說要有天主教徒的話
I'm sure you must know that
我相信你一定知道就是說
catholic this one
天主教這一個
as far as
至於迄今為止
what you believe
你很相信的是
this one
這一個
The so-called homeless big bible
所謂的無家大本聖經
OK Homeless Large Bible
OK 無家大本聖經
What about the Big Homeless Bible?
那無家大本聖經呢
It's very different from this Protestant Bible.
跟這個新教的聖經是很不一樣的
OK
OK
The Big Homeless Bible has 73 volumes in total
無家大本聖經這個總共有73卷
So he translated 567 volumes
所以他翻譯了567卷
These 36 volumes are equal to 567 volumes
這36卷等於567卷的
Homeless Big Book, this Bible
無家大本這個聖經啊
In fact, only a small part remains
其實只剩下一名小部分
This one didn't turn over
這一個沒有翻而已啦
OK
OK
He is not only in a translation of the bible
他不僅僅在一個翻譯聖經
He also commented on the Bible
他同時有註解聖經
OK Commentary Bible
OK 註解聖經
so
所以啊
Inside the 36 volumes
這36卷裡面啊
36 volumes
36卷
When I go to the academic association, I often say that when I go to see this one.
我到學家會常說我這一個去看的時候啊
I found it was volume 36
我發覺是36卷
uh how to say we come back
呃 怎麼說 我們回來
do the math
算了一下
More than 1.5 million words
超過150萬個字
OK
OK
how many money
何金貸
When this agent completes this is at least 36 rolls
在這個代理什麼時候完成這個至少是36卷
OK, it is still a difficult time to scrutinize
OK 現在還是一個很難推敲的一個時間
about the only way we can say
我們大概唯一可以怎麼說
make a little guess
稍微做一點小小的一個猜測
Probably around 1805
時間點大概是1805年左右
why i say 1805
為什麼我說1805年呢
because in 1803
因為1803年的時候
He Jinnai once wrote a letter to the Holy See, but the letter did not go
賀金奈曾經寫信到教廷的傳信不去
Catholicism is different from ordinary Christian denominations
天主教跟一般的基督教的教派不大一樣
Catholicism is a centralized and large system
天主教是一個中央集權的一個很大的體系
You don't understand anything in theory
什麼事情理論上你都不懂
I think I should get to the Holy See
我好像應該到達教廷那一邊
there is the Holy See
有教廷那一邊
Especially when the pope decides to say
尤其是教皇來決定說
can
可否
OK
OK
so
所以
He Jinnaita
賀金奈他
After reversing thirty-six volumes
逆了三十六卷之後
he wrote
他就寫信
in 1803
1803年的時候
He wrote to the Holy See
他就寫信到教廷去
explain
說
Can I limit my subjects?
我可不可以限科
I dug it out now
我現在翻出來的
Thirty-six volumes
三十六卷
OK
OK
He Jinnai is very
賀金奈很
I think he might be more
我覺得他可能比較
naive
天真一點
he should know
他應該知道
The Magic Horse Church is actually
魔馬教會其實在
If i remember correctly
如果我沒記錯的話
around 1612
是1612年左右
OK
OK
the pope
這個教宗
just ban
就下令禁止
This is in various dialects
這個以各地的方言
That is to say, the national languages ​​of various countries
也就是說各國的國語
to translate this nerve
來翻譯這個神經
only one nerve
神經只有一種
Not Hebrew
也不是 Hebrew
Nor is it Greek
也不是 Greek
OK is Latin
OK 是 Latin
So why did He Jinnai not gamble?
所以賀金奈為什麼會無賭
That is to say no gambling in the ban of 1612
就是說無賭於1612年的禁令
This he went to China
這個他到了中國
he translates nerves over there
他在那邊翻譯神經
this is an interesting question
這是一個很有趣的問題
But I can't give you an answer
可是我沒辦法給各位解答
I can only say that He Jinnai's first one might be a little too naive
我只能夠說賀金奈第一個可能太天真了一點
Because the Holy See has lifted the ban
因為教廷已經解禁了
Because it's been a long time
因為時間已經相隔了滿久了
Now it makes sense to think so.
那現在這種以為其實是有道理的
Because the few Western missionaries who were in Beijing at that time
因為當時在北京的這幾個西方的傳教士
In fact, they are under strict supervision.
其實他們被看管得很嚴
OK
OK
you can't talk nonsense
你不能說得亂走的
You can only go to and from get off work every day
你每天只能上班下班
get off work
班下班
ok you are a painter
ok 你是畫師
ok, then you go to this Ruyi Pavilion in Yueming Garden every day
ok 那你每天就到約命園的這個如意館
to draw
去畫畫
What about painting culture?
畫文化之後呢
you should go home
你就該回家了
ok then you want this one to write back to this one's home country
ok 那你想要這一個寫信回這一個本國
ok your family and so on
ok 你的家人等等之類的
you can't say like we write now
你不能夠說像我們現在寫信
Write something and I will lose this mailbox
寫一些我這郵箱就一丟
ok no such thing
ok 沒這一回事
ok, you have to send it to a unit of the Ministry of Internal Affairs
ok 你必須要送到內務府的一個單位去
There's nothing wrong with checking from there
由那邊檢查沒有問題了
ok of course
ok 那當然
uh you didn't write this one
呃 你沒有文這一個
say now
比方說說現在
uh its italian better than french
呃 它義大利文比法文還要好
ok if you want to write in italian
ok 要寫義大利文的話
probably no one over there will be able to check his italian
那邊可能沒有人能夠檢查他的義大利文
Uh, but maybe go to another Jesuit
呃 可是可能會去找別的耶穌會士來說
What does it mean
這是什麼意思
say something in it
在裡面講些什麼東西
ok finished speaking, if there is no problem
ok 講完了如果說沒有什麼問題的話
Oh, let this letter go
喔 那這一封信就放行
You can go back to this Italian area
你就可以進回這一個義大利區
In this situation, if you think about it
在這種狀況下,你想想看
How many letters can he write in English?
他這個英文能夠寫幾封
Each letter is covered by this party membership
每一封都被這個黨籍
or every letter is checked
或是每一封都被檢查
His English is actually very limited.
他英文其實能寫的這個很有限
Once, once, there was a man named Detianshi
有一次,有一次,有一個叫德天士的一個
A Catholic missionary who forgot his nationality
一個忘了國籍的這個天主教傳教士
He has not been taught
他就沒有經過這個教
Sorry, this clear procedure
對不起,這個清清楚楚的這一道手續
he took this one
他就帶著這一個
This letter from several missionaries
好幾個傳教士的這個信
I want to say, OK, I will entrust another Chinese
想說,OK,我就托另外一個中國人
Because he is going to the EU
因為他要到歐盟去
OK, I will entrust him, when this one goes to the EU
OK,我就托他,這一個到歐盟去的時候
By the way, please send me this letter from the European Union.
那順便這個信就幫我們從歐盟這裏寄我去
send it, all right
寄出去,好啦
This becomes a Jia Qingxiang
這就變成了一個家慶祥
the very famous Detus case
非常出名的德天士案
OK
OK
Detianshi did it because of this
德天士因爲這樣子做
he was old
他被老改了
OK
OK
sent this heat
送了這個熱合
Go to the South China Sea to share hardships
去南海邊做苦共
It took five or six years to return to Beijing
做了五六年才歸這一個北京去
So they were
所以他們那個時候
in Beijing
在北京
Although it is said that East, West, North and South Church
雖然說東西南北堂
But this kind of connection with the Holy See
可是跟教廷之間的這種connection
Actually not very strong
其實並不是很強的
So I miss Mrs. He Jin
所以我想賀金太太
she doesn't know
她根本不知道
For example, the Holy See is
比如說教廷是
Unban or not yet
解禁還是還沒有解禁
she is in beijing anyway
她反正在北京
she's fine
她先都沒事
She came home after painting
她畫了畫之後回到家裡面
except for a prayer
除了拜一拜之外
I'll just be there the rest of the time
我其他時間就只好在那邊
How to say
怎麼說
over there this translation
在那邊這個翻譯
Bible
聖經
This must also be correct
這個還必須要correct
a very
一個大家非常
a wrong concept
錯誤的一個概念
I just say
我就說
the old missionary
這個舊教的傳教士
It doesn't seem to translate this nerve
好像都不翻譯這個神經的
OK Protestants don’t understand this old religion very much.
OK 新教徒於這一點是很不諒解這一個舊教的
OK, many scholars actually meet the requirements
OK 那很多學者其實也符合
This Protestant saying
這個新教的說法的
OK I want to look at it from an academic point of view
OK 我想從學術的角度來看
Guxin's nerves came out today
今天古新神經跑出來了
We should say there is nothing wrong old teacher
我們應該說沒有錯 舊教師
Of course, this nerve has not been given rights and interests to complete
當然沒有把這個神經給權益完成
But someone from the old teacher had that motive
可是舊教師有人有那個動機
have that attempt
有那個attempt
OK have that attempt
OK 有那個企圖
he wants rights
他想要權益
This martial arts Osaka this nerve
這個武教大阪這個神經
this nerve of their belief
他們信仰的這個神經
ok so i figured this out
OK 所以我想這一點
possible
可能
The neuroresearch community
這個神經研究界
I need to go to the hearing for a while
要稍微去聽證一些
the old idea
以往的這個觀念
OK
OK
just mentioned that is to say
剛剛提到就是說
because I really don't know
因為我實在是不知道
hello christmas when is this
賀聖誕是什麼時候這個
How can I say it? It's hard to understand.
怎麼說 聽理不易的啦
OK
OK
I can probably only speculate that
我大概只能夠推測就是說
He sent this letter in 1803
他1803年送出去這個信件
With the traffic conditions at that time
以當時的這個交通狀況
In 1803, there were no booster ships
1803年的時候還沒有增機船
OK
OK
The booster ship may have come around 1820
增機船可能還來到1820年左右
so he should be
所以他應該是
It should be this general this
應該是這個一般的這個
normal ship
一般的這個輪船
OK
OK
That
那
this letter
這個一封信
To pray from this pan-terrestrial tank of this Chinese offering
要從這個中國祭祷的這個泛地缸
In fact, I will calculate for him
其實我給他算算
It should be at least two years
至少應該要兩年的這個時間
OK for two years
OK 兩年的時間
So even if he is 1805
所以就算他是1805年
OK
OK
36 donations for his pan-terrestrial tank
他這個泛地缸36捐
but a little worried
可是有點不大放心
OK
OK
Give him another three years
再給他增加三年吧
so i this
所以我這個
I said lower limit
我說是下限
maybe 1808
或許是1808年
how can i say maybe
我怎麼會說或許
to 1790
到1790年
is almost a certain point in time
是幾乎是確定的一個時間點
OK
OK
That's because
那因為
He is in this period
他就在這一段期間裡面
In the past ten years
這十幾年裡面
He turned the whole date over.
他把就約整個翻出來了
what about the new covenant
新約呢
In fact, most of them are translated
其實也大部分都翻譯了
OK
OK
And the translation is quite interesting
而且譯得相當有趣
i think we can take a look
我想我們可以看一張
This picture of the new testament is good
這個新約的這個圖片好了
OK
OK
This is what we call Genesis
這個是我們所謂的創世記
what we call genesis today
我們今天所謂的創世記
the word creation
創世這兩個字
I haven't done my research
我還沒有好好做研究
but i'm going to answer
不過我要去回答
possibly from
有可能是從
Luewen turned around
略文那邊轉過來的
OK
OK
I don't know very well
我不是很清楚啦
but
但是
What about He Jintai?
賀金泰呢
I'm sure he's a bible
我確定他是一個對聖經
someone who knows very well
非常了解的一個人
because
因為啊
Today's biblical studies
今天這個聖經學界啊
research community
研究界啊
often think that say ah
常常認為說啊
this
這個
What about Genesis?
這個創世紀呢
There are actually two stories
實際上是有兩個故事
pieced together
拼湊起來的
OK
OK
That
那
What about He Jintai?
賀金泰呢
he put this
他把這個
This Genesis
這個創世紀啊
He is a brave protector
他這個膽大保護天
honestly
坦白說
his genesis he divided
他的創世紀他分成
one knife two paragraphs
一刀兩段
just cut in two
只是砍成兩部分
two
兩個
two volumes
兩卷
OK
OK
god made man
上帝製造人類
everything else
其他萬物
He is called the gene of formation
他叫做化成之基因
OK
OK
Of course it turns into these two words
當然化成這兩個字呢
turned into heaven and earth
是化成天地
This saying should come from the Yijing
這個話應該是從義經來的
Painted as heaven and earth or waist
畫成天地還是腰子
this one from over there
這一個那邊來的
After this human being begins to recover
這個人類開始還原之後
Create a variety of different carriages
創造各種不同的馬車
utensils
器皿
etc
等等之類的
Then this face-changing of human beings themselves
然後人類自己本身的這個翻顏
Abraham's fingering and all that stuff
亞伯拉罕的指說等等之類的
what about that part
那一部分呢
It's called the Sutra of Creation
它叫做造成之經
OK
OK
So in a sense
所以某個意義上來講
I miss He Jinnai
我想賀金奈
He Jinnai is more sensitive
賀金奈是比較大感一點
Actually cut the bible like this
居然把這個聖經這樣子給腰砍腰斬了
I don't believe it after that
之後我就不相信說
If he said that the preaching of the Roman Way
他如果說這個傳經羅馬道
This copy of an Old New Bible
這一份的一個古新聖經
If there are people who know Chinese in the Roman Road
如果傳經羅馬道也有人這個懂中文的話
I can't believe this one they will unify
我不敢相信這一個他們會統一
This publication of this book
這本書的這個 publication
OK
OK
He still burns him out
他還是把他火絕掉了
no matter what
那不管怎麼樣
we see
我們就看到
He Jindai
賀金黛
he this
他這個
new moon night
新月一晚
Employment? It's about the same.
就業呢 業也差不多了
then this is
那這是
We are all familiar
我們大家比較熟悉的
So I edited this picture out
所以我把這一張圖片給修出來
you can see
你們可以看到
this
這個
at first
起初
At first it was
起初是
From martial arts to heaven and earth
從武而化成天地
Then the earth is empty and bare
然後地是空虛而又光光的
dark shadow
又昏暗黑影
on extremely deep surface
在極深的處理面上
Holy Spirit
斗屍的聖神
walking on water
在水上行走著
this i think
這個我想
If there are Christians doing this again
如果再做這個有基督徒的話
to this
對這個
This paragraph should be
這一段話應該是
more familiar than me
比我還要熟的
OK
OK
Fighting dead is the Latin Deus
斗屍是拉丁人的這個Deus
In fact, it is the consciousness of God
其實就是神的這個意識
that's actually
那其實在
Nemesis generation this era
克星代這個時代
He is actually not supposed to use Shake Corpse
他是實際上是不應該用抖尸的
he used god
他用天主
He should have used the word God
他應該用天主這兩個字才對
OK
OK
Because it was still in the Ming Dynasty in 1627
因為1627年的時候還在明朝
in 1627
1627年的時候
this
這個
Some of the larger
當時的一些比較大
The more important one is the Jesuit
比較重要的這一個耶穌會士
For example, like Long Huangping
比如說像龍皇平
high character
高一字
Jin Yige wait for these Jesuits
金一格等等這些耶穌會士
When they were in 1627
他們在1627年的時候
they are in the family this one
他們在家庭這一個
Shanghai
上海
Shanghai family place
上海家庭那個地方
where they meet
他們在那邊會合
11 Jesuits
11個耶穌會士
in 1627
1627年的時候
Xu Guang's early days
徐光其底之早
Yang Tingwen, they are still there
楊廷文他們都還在
they also practice
他們也練習
give opinions
提供意見
they debate over there
他們在那邊辯論
OK
OK
What are you arguing about?
辯論什麼東西呢
OK, low big evil
OK,低大邪
How exactly should I translate
到底專門應該怎麼樣翻譯
OK, how to translate
OK,要怎麼翻譯
Are you going to translate to this one
你是要翻譯成為這一個
Well
呃
uh god
呃,上帝
or translated as God
或是翻譯成為天主
OK, uh, or translated into
OK,呃,或是翻譯成為
uh, you just use
呃,你就乾脆用
English translation
英譯把
are you calling it
你是把它叫做
Doos and Fighters
Doos跟斗士
English is similar, or you want
英也差不多,或是說你要
Hurry up and call Doos
快一點的話,就叫Doos
OK, uh, I want
OK,呃,我要
anyway, uh
anyway,呃
this one two thousand years
這個,一個二千年
These people reached the final conclusion
這些人到最後的這個結論
yes
是
uh, this, they have been
呃,這個,都一直他們
win, ok, that is to say
勝出,OK,也就是說
uh, they think this
呃,他們覺得這個
Doos should be translated as God
Doos應該翻譯成為天主
OK, that
OK,那
What about Luo Wenning's faction?
羅文寧這一派呢
It was a failure because Luo Wenning
算是失敗了,因為羅文寧
This pie, then I am Chinese
這派,那我中國
There is no equivalent to this Doos at all
根本沒有相等於這個Doos
this concept of this
這個概念的這個
uh uh
呃,呃
name
名稱
So Meng Wanping insisted that
所以孟晚平是堅持說
Since there is no
既然沒有的話
Then it should be translated in a responsive way
那麼就應該用因應的方式來翻譯
OK
OK
It's just that Meng Wanping doesn't
只是孟晚平這個沒有
did not succeed
沒有成功
this He Jintai
這個賀金泰
possible
可能
when he translated
他翻譯的時候
Maybe he has his own considerations
可能有他自己的這個考量
OK
OK
When he translated this Deus
他翻譯這個Deus的時候
he always
他一律呢
still
還是
He followed Meng Wanping
他是跟著孟晚平走的
He translates as a Deus
他翻譯成個Deus
Translated into a Dou Shi Dou Sister
翻譯成個斗師斗姐
only when encountering some
只有在碰到一些
When not the word Deus
不是Deus的這個字的時候
He will switch to other usage
他才會換成其他的這個用法
for example
比方說
Deus
Deus
The word Deus
Deus這個字
Dominus
Dominus
In fact, it is the consciousness of the Lord
其實就是主的意識
ok main
OK 主
the Lord
上主
the master
那個主
How am I aware?
我哪個意識啦
Like Dominionist, he turned it into this group
像Dominionist他就把它翻成這個組
Sometimes he is different into the upper group
有些時候他異成上組
this
這個
he is all we know
他是我們所知道的
Until now
到現在為止
first discussed in China
第一個在中國討論起
This so-called Teachable Grammation
這個所謂Teachable Grammation
the first person with a so-called very good question
所謂甚好問題的第一人
Although it is said that Mohangnian had already started to debate in 1627
雖然說Mohangnian在1627年的時候就已經開始辯論了
But this person who will discuss all the holy names
可是會去把所有的聖號都拿出來討論的這個人
is the core station
是核心臺
he even
他甚至
I don't like the ones in the middle
中間那些我就不團了
He's even in one of his teaching assistants for the Paleo Bible
他甚至在他的古形聖經的一個助教裡面
He said
他說
this
這個
this Java
這個Java
Whether you can still fire in a night
不管你還能在一個夜火
Or modern people change their name to Yahweh
或是現代人翻名耶和華
He Jin told you
賀金都告訴你說
This Dos warrior has no tacit understanding of this name
這個Dos的武士是沒有默契過這個名字的
In fact, the name is from the 16th century.
其實這個名字是16世紀的時候
just synthesized a name
才合成的一個名字
Protestants have been using this name
新教就一直驗用這個名字
so you're in the old bible
所以你在舊教的聖經裡面
The name Jehovah cannot be found
是找不到耶和華這個名字的
He Jin did a lot of this type of work anyway
那 anyway 賀金做了很多這一類型的工作
So I said that within 1.5 million words
所以我說150萬字裡面
About a quarter of them are annotations
大概有四分之一是註解
This quarter of the note is very important
這四分之一的註解是非常重要的
Because after China succeeded Yang Maluo
因為中國繼陽馬羅之後
Yang Marlowe's Straightforward Explanation of the Bible
陽馬羅的聖經直解
that is not a complete bible
那不是一部完整的聖經
that's part of the bible
那是部分的聖經
Bible Straightforward
聖經直解
After that, in a very large Bible
之後呢 一部非常大的聖經裡面
Refer to a book with a lot of annotations
參找了非常多的註解的一本書
So I think this is
所以我覺得這個是
if i'm free that day
我那天有空的話
I want to write an article called "He Jintai's Theory of Lifting the Ban"
我要寫一篇文章叫做《賀金太的解禁學》
because I feel that some places
因為我覺得有些地方
He Jintai may have told them the interpretation of the Church of Rome
賀金太恐怕已經跟他們羅馬教會的詮釋
there is some distance
是有一些距離了
he has his own opinion
他有他自己的看法
Let alone coming to China
更何況來到中國
It's unlikely that you don't have your own opinion.
沒有自己的看法那也不大可能的
That text by He Jintai
那賀金太的這個文字
what is it like
是怎樣子的一回事呢
I think we'll look at this first
我想我們先看一下這個
"Holy Mother Hopes for You" Mo Zhimeng is ready
《聖母熱的望你》莫之夢好了
This is the preface of his "No Spirit Sutra"
這是他的這個《無精神經》的序言
This is also the prologue
這也是序言
In total he wrote two parts of this preface to the Old and New Bibles
他總而為古新聖經寫了兩篇的這個序語言
He even how the Bible should be typeset
他連這個聖經到底應該要怎麼排版
We call typesetting today
我們今天叫排版
He made it very clear
他都規定得很清楚
you want to add one line you want to add two lines
你要加一條線 要加兩條線
you want a frame
你要畫框框
where to use small print
什麼地方用小字
In fact, he made it very clear in his preamble.
他這序語語裡面其實都講得很清楚
But what?
不過呢
What I value most is the dream of St. Gerald and Ning Lonely
我最看重的還是聖熱落寧寞之夢
this place
這個地方
St. Geraldine
聖熱落寧寞教外的人士
this may be unfamiliar
這可能比較不熟
non-religious people wait
教外人士等戰
Non-religious people should be familiar with a name called
教外人士應該熟一個名字叫做
Sanger Room
Sanger Room
holy
聖
Jer Room
Jer Room
Anyway
Anyway
Shengre Luo Ning Lone is the Sanger Room
聖熱落寧寞就是Sanger Room
Definitely this one of the five big bibles
絕對是這五家大本聖經的這一個
How do you say this
這個怎麼說
Interested person
意者
ok
ok
That Kowloon
那九龍這個
this
這個
It is said
據說啦
That Kowloon is a very good Latin guy
那九龍是一個拉丁人非常好的一個人
ok
ok
That
那
It is said that he
據說這個他
When we start translating the Bible
開始翻譯這個聖經的時候啊
Well he is the same as this
那麼他是一樣這個
a very beautiful this
一首非常漂亮的這個
The problem with Cicero
西賽羅時的這個問題啊
translate this bible
翻譯這個聖經
ok
ok
That
那
this bible
這個聖經
Can you translate like this?
容得你這樣翻譯嗎
this is a big problem
這是一個很大的一個問題
I'll miss him later
等一下我還會想他
Then anyway when he translates like this
那anyway他這樣翻譯的時候啊
How long has it been?
發了沒多久呢
Eh
欸
we say so
我們這麼講啦
one day he was sleeping
有一天他在睡覺
ok
ok
in sleep
睡夢之中呢
god god nerve
天神天神經
turned into an angel today
今天翻成天使
just a few angels
就好幾個天使
that's a whip
那是鞭子
You guys still have mace
各位還有狼牙棒
this philosophy
這個哲對
then hit him
然後邊打他
Hit until you hit this mixed injury
打到打到這混身之傷
While beating him, he laughed and said
一面打一面就激笑他說
You are the disciple of C15
你是C15的這個disciple門帝
we're here for the shit
我們特別來抽屎
come to get you
來抽到你
Just hit him with this
就是打他一頓這個
as this bag
當作這個籌包
nine people wake up
九人這個醒過來
Of course it hurts to be beaten
被打到一頓當然是很痛
wake up soon
馬上就醒過來了
after waking up
醒過來之後
Those Angels are gone
那些Angels都不見了
Nine is Saint
九人是Saint
saint
聖人
Catholic Fort the Saint
天主教堡這個Saint
translates to saint
翻譯成為聖人
saint he feels pain all over
聖人他混身覺得疼
Maybe he also finds himself mixed
能夠他也發覺自己混身
there is that edge mark
有那個邊痕
I fell out of bed wondering if he was sleeping
我在猜想他是不是睡覺的時候從床上跌下來
OK
OK
anyway
anyway
all in all
總而言之
the whole long time
整個久遠
Only then did I realize that
這個時候才了解到說
oh
喔
this translated bible
這個翻譯聖經
I won't ask which kind of prettiest this one
我不會問那一種最漂亮的這一個
this problem
這個問題
style
style
or style
或者style
OK
OK
to translate
來翻譯
Of course there is a reason for this
那當然這是有這一個原因的啦
OK
OK
Two appointments in the New Territories
這個新界兩約啊
The interval of about 500 years in the middle
中間相隔的這個500年左右的這個時間
What about the Old Testament era?
那舊約的時代呢
Actually most people
其實大部分人
Don't say people like Jesus and others
不要說像耶穌等等他們這些人
In fact, many people are shepherds.
其實很多人都是牧羊人啊
OK
OK
shepherd you expect him this one
牧羊人你期待他這一個
including the heretics
包括邪經人
OK
OK
How high do you expect him to be in this deal?
你期待他這個交易程度有多高
Then they are here all day and night
那他們一天到晚在這裡
There's one that's sloppy, etc.
有一個有盪啦等等之類的
OK Shepherd, boil water and grass but refuse
OK 牧羊 煮水草而拒
OK, tell me how good this kind of education they can be
OK 你說他們能夠有多好的這一種教育啊
I think this is a big problem
我想這是一個很大的一個問題啦
OK so how to say
OK 所以怎麼說
uh this
呃 這個
So this is a date
所以這個就約啊
Just ask everyone not to think of it as saying
就約大家不要把它想像成為說
Of course, it is a question as great as our Fourteenth Five-Year Classics.
就約當然是類似我們十四五經這個那麼偉大的這個問題
uh written stuff
呃 寫出來的東西
Then it's quite, uh, how to say this?
那就約這個是相當呃 怎麼說
The language of the book is quite reasonable.
相當理書的這個語言這個寫的
OK although I don't understand Hebrew
OK 雖然我不懂 Hebrew
But to understand this uh
可是為了解這個呃
Just make an appointment, it is written in a language that is quite reasonable
就約啊是用相當理書的這個語言這個寫成的
except for the whole
整個就約除了
middle two exceptions
中間兩個例外
San Yongji and this
聖永吉還有這個
Uh, it's commonly known as locking our prince brother's
呃 通稱鎖了我們王子哥的
OK
OK
part of this thing
部分的這一個東西
ok
ok
that is poetry
那是詩
of course it's impossible
那當然不可能
Tata Tata
用太太太
too vulgar to write in this language
太粗俗的這一個語言來寫
The others
其他呢
this is recommended
建議要的這個
Wrong place to start
穿錯之地開始
actually follow
其實都跟
not so
沒有那麼
That is to say, the style is
就是說那個文體都是
are all comparisons
都是都是比較
lower level
比較低層次的
ok
ok
and you
那你
think about it
你想想看這
when jesus was twelve
耶穌十二歲的時候
just come out and follow one
就出來跟著一個
At that time, there was this teacher of the Tairen
當時有太人的這個經師
debate over there in the temple
在廟裡面在那邊辯論
ok
ok
a twelve year old boy
一個十二歲的小孩
how smart is jesus
耶穌在怎麼聰明吧
Just think about a twelve year old kid
你想想看一個十二歲的小孩
we today
我們今天
Our twelve-year-old boy today
我們今天十二歲的小孩
you speak out
你講出
what great words did you say
你講出什麼偉大的話出來呢
ok
ok
jesus may be an exception
耶穌可能例外
He may speak of some of the greater
他可能會講出一些比較偉大的
these words come out
這些話出來
But those of his contemporaries
但是跟他同時代的那些人
How can there be such a skill?
哪有這種本領啊
so
所以
This part about this is actually quite reasonable.
這個就約這一部分其實是相當理書的這一種
The so-called vulgarism
所謂vulgarism
ok this kind of question
ok 這樣子的一種這個問題
written ok
寫成的 ok
It's hard to tell about the appointment
心約呢比較難講
What about the spirit of writing?
心約的寫精神呢
varying levels of education
教育程度不一
ok, for example, the Gospel of Matthew, this Matthew
ok 比方說馬太福音們這一個馬太
Ma Dou La
馬豆啦
catholic horse beans
天主教教馬豆
ok horse bean gospel
ok 馬豆福音
Ma Dou is a person with a very good education
馬豆是一個手國相當好的這個教育的人
ok the Gospel of John that's another story
ok 約翰福音那又是另外一回事啦
john is a dreamer
約翰是一個作夢
dreaming all day long
一天到晚在作夢
one crashed
一個當機啦
ok and he's a crash
ok 而且他是一個當機
So his text compares
所以他的文字就比較
more vulgar
比較粗俗一點
ok, what about the letter collection
ok 那書信集呢
Letters
書信集
The biggest trick in the letter collection is Paul.
書信集裡面最大招的是保羅啊
ok paul
ok 保羅
ok paul this them
ok 保羅這個他們
Catholics don't teach Paul
天主教不教保羅啦
ok catholic another
ok 天主教另外一個
this lecture
這個講法
like the words of paul
像保羅的話
Paul is a senior intellectual
保羅是一個高級知識分子
He was very well trained in monasticism
他受過非常好的修士學的訓練
So Paul's epistles
所以保羅的書信
he wrote nine letters
他寫了九封信
Wrote nine letters to Canadians
寫了九封信給加拿大人
to the romans
給羅馬人
give where where where
給哪裡哪裡哪裡
connecting the entire mediterranean
串聯整個地中海
all the way to australia
一直到澳洲
nine cities
九個城市
Christians
的基督徒
string it together
把它串聯起來
so actually
所以實際上
I should say so
我應該這樣講吧
this catholic
這個天主教
Jesus didn't invent it
並不是耶穌發明的
not created by him
不是祂創立的
Jesus actually thought he was a
耶穌其實認為祂是一個
How to say
怎麼說
a prophet in Judaism
是猶太教裡面的一個先知
This is his definition of who he is
這是祂對祂自己的身分的界定
really take this catholic
真正把這個天主教
or to put the thought of jesus
或者說把耶穌的思想
believers in jesus
信耶穌的人
this person connected
串聯起來的這個人
it's paul
是保羅
It was Paul's contribution
是保羅的這個貢獻
So we often say that Paul is
所以我們常常說保羅才是
true founder of catholicism
天主教真正的創立者
jesus is not
耶穌並不是
OK
OK
then anyway what i want to say is to say
那anyway我要說的就是說
paul he is actually a
保羅他實際上是一個
a man who is very well trained in rhetoric
受過非常好的修辭學訓練的一個人
especially experienced
尤其是受過
The so-called judicial rhetoric
那種所謂judicial rhetoric
OK
OK
This training in courtroom rhetoric
法庭修辭學的這個訓練
in court like a lawyer
就像律師一樣在庭上
able to talk to others
能夠跟人家
debate with others
跟人家辯論
OK
OK
He's been very well trained in this area
他受過非常好的這一方面的這個訓練
So the Pauline letter is
所以那個保羅書信寫的是
it is written
寫的是
How to say Wang Yang knowledge
怎麼說汪洋知識
OK
OK
this one
這一個
this kind
這種
this reasoning
這種推理
OK
OK
debate
辯論
It's almost diabolical
它是幾乎是口惡宣核啊
ok let you down
ok 讓你栽架不住
make you feel say
讓你覺得說
Anyway, what you said seems to be the most correct.
反正你講的話好像最具都是對的
ok, so the wish is a bit more difficult to say
ok 所以心願是比較難講一點
It's different when you go to the Discrimination Register
你到歧視錄那又不一樣啦
The discrimination record is actually made by the local one.
歧視錄其實也是當地這一個做出來的
this one this book
這一個這一部書
Sorry, I have Tian Bishops here.
對不起啊 我在這有田主教徒
I'm christian
我是基督徒
because i'm not a gangster
因為我不是什麼徒
I sometimes speak and compare
我有些時候會講話會比較
From the point of view of our secular world
從我們這種世俗界的角度來看
Discrimination record you all know
歧視錄你們都知道
The discriminatory record is only inside
歧視錄只是裡面
It's all a myth, isn't it?
裡面其實都是神話嘛 對不對
The issue of discrimination
歧視錄的這個問題
That style is quite low style
那個style就是相當low的style
That is to say it is not very elegant style
就是說它不是很高雅的style
ok so wish it had this
ok 所以心願它有這個
it doesn't have to
它不一定
it has elegance
它有的高雅
Some are lower
有的這個比較低一點
ok so this congratulatory belt
ok 所以這個賀金帶
He's pretty awesome
他還蠻厲害的 他這個
When he met this Xinyue
他在遇到這個心悅的時候啊
he will become a problem
他會變問題
OK he will be a problem
OK 他會變問題
This is what we have been teaching students on the translation
這個是我們在翻譯上面 我們一直教學生說
I am in the Institute of Translation Research
我本人是在翻譯研究所這個
Persevere OK
堅持的 OK
Then I often teach students that
那我常常在教學生說
You can translate consciousness
你這個把意識給翻譯出來啊
It's just a basic job
那只是一個最基本的一個工作而已
What you should really be doing is
你其實真正應該這個做的工作是
Translate people's questions
把人家的問題給翻譯出來
Translate other people's style
把人家的style給翻譯出來
that's it
那這樣才算是
To complete this job of this translation, let's say
完成這個翻譯的這個工作 比方說吧
OK
OK
We have too much of this in foreign countries
我們太多的這個在國外的這個
sinologist
漢學家
OK
OK
Whether Chinese or foreigners
中國人也好外國人也好
78 weeks after this was dug out
78禮拜這個翻出來之後
After Du Fu was dug out again, there was no difference between Du Fu that week.
再把杜甫翻出來之後 那個禮拜杜甫根本沒什麼差別的
OK
OK
What about us in Taiwan?
那在我們台灣呢
same ok
一樣啦 OK
Then lose the round British 19th century romantic teacher
然後敗輪英國19世紀浪漫師人
Number kids19th century romantic teacher
Number kids19世紀浪漫師人
You learned this shirley from a 19th century romantic teacher
你把這個shirley學來19世紀浪漫師人
After you translate it into Chinese
你把它翻成中文之後
Those three people are also a total of one person
那三個人也是一共一個人
Turned out that the English style is gone
翻出來那個英文的style都不見了
You just pass the message out
你只是把message傳遞出來而已
Then send this message
那這訊息傳遞出來
problem didn't come out
問題沒有帶出來
So how can you say your translation is a successful one?
那你怎麼能夠說你的翻譯是一個成功的翻譯呢
you turn to the end you will find
你翻到最後你會發覺
if say you have some translators
如果說你有一些翻譯家
when he went on
他繼續走下去的時候
You find that what he translates is actually
你發覺他翻譯的東西其實
His translation of SARS Biya is quite anti-French
他翻SARS比亞也是蠻有反法
That is to say, the first-class SARS Biya
也是說一流的SARS比亞
Follow him to read second-rate and third-rate Western writers
跟他翻二流和三流的西方作家
The problem is the same style is the same
問題是一樣的style是一樣的
this change
這個變化
it's a pity
這是很可惜的一件事情
But it's hard to teach students
不過很難教導學生
Let them fully understand this style
讓他們完全能夠明白這個style
how important
有多重要
Naga Jinna is very clear
那賀金奈是非常清楚
this one person
這一點的一個人
This dream that actually gave birth to Jerome
實際上生Jerome的這個dream
this dream
這個夢
In fact, posterity later inspected this textual research
其實後人這個後來考察這個考證
Jerome's dream
Jerome的這個夢
actually sitting here
其實是坐在這個
he started this translation bible
他開始這個翻譯聖經
years ago
以前好幾年
Ok
Ok
So he actually translated the Bible with this
所以其實跟這個他翻譯聖經
it doesn't matter
是沒有什麼關係的
But in the end it will be our human ability
不過後會是我們人的這個本領
Ok
Ok
this history of translation
這個翻譯史
Just take this Jerome's dream
就把這個Jerome的這個dream
Ok
Ok
Why use this with Jerome
跟Jerome這個為什麼要用
so-called general book
所謂的通書的
Latin to translate the bible
拉丁文來翻譯聖經
just combine it
就把它結合起來了
OK
OK
the useless one
絕用的那一本
this bible
這一個聖經
This is called Homeless Big Ben
這個叫無家大本
this is chinese
這是中文
OK in English
OK 英文講叫
The Vulgate Bible
The Vulgate Bible
OK
OK
The Latin word for English is called
英文這個拉丁文講叫
Knife
Wukade
OK
OK
this homeless man
這個無家大本
this bible
這一個聖經
where is the big homeless bible
無家大本聖經呢
this
這個
no
不是
this one
這一個
how to say that
那一種怎麼說
similar
類似
similar to this one
類似這一個
Plaintext
平文
OK
OK
Or
或者說
similar
類似
don't speak plain language
不要說平文
It doesn't even look like stereotyped essays
連八股文它都不像
OK
OK
it is totally used
它完全全是用
in the market
市場裡面的
those
那一些
so-called peddling
所謂販富走足
The so-called speculators who sell ginger
所謂引測賣薑者流
OK
OK
It's the mother-in-law in the market
就是市場裡面的婆婆媽媽
them
他們
translate this bible in their words
用他們的話來翻譯這個聖經
So five big bibles
所以五家大本聖經
The five big bibles are in the era of about
五家大本聖經是在紀元大概
around the fourth century
四世紀左右的時候
this Yoshimaru
這個義丸的
Tunnel fifth century
坑道五世紀
I don't know remember
我不知道記得
Because after Yoshimaru
因為他義丸之後
until this
接下來一直到這個
Probably around 1592
大概是1592年左右
In fact, the whole of Europe
其實整個歐洲
They all believe in the five major Bibles
都是信仰這本五家大本聖經
Because this is the Church of Rome
因為這是教會羅馬教會
signed this bible
簽訂的這個聖經
you don't need to understand greek
你可以不懂希臘文
you don't need to understand spanish
你可以不懂西班牙文
but you have to understand
可是你必須要懂
you can read this bible in latin
拉丁文你才能夠讀這個聖經
otherwise
要不的話
you don't understand latin
你不懂拉丁文
You can at least pronounce that too
你至少會發音那也可以
So
那麼
Translated five large Bibles
翻譯了五家大本聖經
is the translation of the Middle Ages throughout Europe
是翻譯了整個歐洲的中世紀
until 1592
一直到1592年的時候
At that time, it was called Kermit Barst
那個時候叫皇叫Kermit Barst
he just thought
他才覺得說
It seems that throughout the Middle Ages
好像因為在整個中世紀
As long as Gutenberg invented printing in 1550
只要在1550年古藤堡發明印刷術
before 1550
在1550年之前
In fact, what you read about Jiuwenteng
其實大家讀的九文藤的東西
It's all this superbook
都是這個超本
It's all super on the central grape
都是超在央提子上的
Ultrabooks are a big problem
超本的問題是很大的
some people more than one word
有些人超出過一個字
Some people have one more word and one less
有些人多一個字少一個字
or not the whole
或是整個就不完
gone, and so on
不見了,等等之類的
how am i
我怎麼樣
is there any such condition
是有任何這個狀況
Can be long, conceivable situation
可以長,可以想像得到的狀況
In fact, most of them will have
其實大部分都會有的
So in 1592 when
所以在1592年的時候
This Climate 80
這個Climate 80
He finally said no
他終於覺得說不行
OK, this must be unified
OK,這個非得統一
This one of the five big books
五家大本的這一個
How to say
怎麼說
His ciphertext is not
他的密文不可
OK, so this one came out in 1592
OK,所以1592年的時候就出現了這一個
that latin family is called
那個拉丁人家叫做
I Kadan Climateenum
我加丹Climateenum
OK, the English translation is called
OK,翻譯英文叫做
Climate times
Climate times
vulgate
vulgate
OK, that is to say
OK,也就是說
This is a Climate book
這一個Climate本
Big Five
五家大本
Bible
聖經
OK
OK
Then I can be 100% sure that
那我可以百分之百的一個確定的是
He Qingpai
賀青派
translate the ancient bible
翻譯這個古形聖經
must be based on
一定是根據
With Gartham, Clementine
有Gartham,Clementine
but
但是
Even if it is this book, the so-called standard text, the Bible
就算是這一本,把這一本所謂的這個標準本,這個聖經
In fact, there are various Versions versions
其實有各種不同的Versions版本
Some have gaps, some don't
有的有差圖,有的沒有差圖
There is this one, with possible punctuation
有的這一個,有可能標點符號
In fact, punctuation marks were rarely used at that time.
其實那時候很少用標點符號
this is late
這個都很晚
so
所以
in the end want
到底要
If we do this today, then we do this today
如果我們今天這個,那我們今天
I already have 36 volumes of this
手上已經有這36卷的這個
this
這個
fruit new bible
果新聖經
Then we're going to find this for the 36 volumes of the Guoxin Bible
那我們要為這36卷的果新聖經去找這個
This is the first book
這個第一本啊
ok
ok
It's not that easy
其實不是那麼容易的一件事情
Why is it not such an easy thing?
為什麼不是那麼容易的一件事情,這原因呢
actually
其實
The reason for this should be your replacement chief.
這原因應該是你們的換理長
ok
ok
The reason is this
這原因呢是這個
There are some libraries in the mainland
大陸有一些圖書館
OK
OK
Until now
到現在為止
Probably not very willing to let you read his book.
大概都還不怎麼願意讓你看他的書
OK
OK
Whether it is He Jin, he has always lived in Beitang
不論是賀金,他一直都是住在北唐的
Bei Tang in Beijing
北京的北唐
Beitang is by the sea, that area, Peking University
北唐是在海邊,那一個區域,北京大學
that area
那一個區域
OK
OK
this North Tang
這個北唐
Actually own a really good one
實際上又自己一個非常棒的一個
The library is like our newer education before
圖書館,就好像以前我們的更新的教育
A pretty awesome library like
一個相當棒的一個圖書館一樣的
Northern Tang Book
北唐書
Northern Tang's book dream
北唐的書夢啊
actually exceeded
其實超了
Shumeng of Beitang, you let go of Shumeng of Beitang, there are quite a few of them
北唐書夢,你放開北唐書夢是有不少的這個
The big price version of this
物價大版的這個
Bible
聖經
The Christian edition of this bible
克安門特版的這個聖經
there are quite a few
也有相當多
also super same
也超同著
even more
更是不少
OK
OK
Where is the dream in this book?
這書夢裡面呢
clearly recorded
記載的清清楚楚
but you have to take
可是你必須要拿
There just happens to be this very, very interesting coincidence
這裡面剛好這個非常非常有趣的一巧合適
i've been watching this
我一直在看這個
Previously this was a magazine published in Zhejiang
以前這個在浙江發行的一本雜誌
It's called "Shangzi Compilation Library Journal"
叫做《上字編譯館刊》
There is still a university in Japan called "Shangzi University", right?
日本現在還有一間大學叫《上字大學》對不對
Then this "Shangzi Compilation Library Journal"
那這《上字編譯館刊》
It contains the special script for Northern Tibet
裡面就刊載了這個北藏的專門書母
Then pointed out that Mrs. He Jin once had a heart attack
然後指出說賀金太太曾經有股心神經
This operation of the 15 cards of the magic guard
這個魔衛的15張的這個操作
Of course, these operations will not be fun later
這些操作當然它不會是後來好玩的
When it's time for the tuition fee, it will take the class by the way.
是課金的時候它順便要課進去的
So in fact, if we say that there is a way
所以我們其實如果說有辦法
Put this North Tibet by the way because those
把這個北藏順便因為那些
so much of this nerve
那麼多的這個神經
Let's match each other
一本來合對一下
If the operation of these 15 cards
如果說這15張的這個操作
if you are there
也在的話
So
那麼
cooperate
合作一下
we all know
我們大家就知道說
Which book is He Jinjia based on
賀金家是根據哪一本
this one
這一個
Well
呃
clament version of this one
克拉曼特版的這一個
Um
嗯
The Five Great Ones
五家大本身經
OK
OK
Well
呃
But because
不過因為
Some
一些
Well
呃
some causes of noise some noise
一些雜訊雜訊的一些原因
OK
OK
so
所以
You have to look for this bibliography in the Northern Collection
你要尋著這一個北藏書目尋找
He Jin’s all this specific version
賀金家所有的這一個特定的這一個版本啊
Well
呃
People in difficulty today from
今天困難人員從從
in ours
在我們
Well
呃
Before Xu Jiahui in this continent
這一個大陸徐家輝之前啊
Xu Jiahui didn't even know that he had a book called
徐家輝是根本不知道他有一本書叫做
old and new biblical
古新聖經的
OK
OK
he has a herb
他有一本草本
called the Old New Bible
叫古新聖經的
Xu Jiahui doesn't know
徐家輝不知道的
OK
OK
so uh
所以呃
How to say
怎麼說
this book
這個底本啊
The basic problem is
底本問題是
a quite
一個相當
big one question
大的一個問題
pretty good
相當好
OK
OK
So
那麼
Well
呃
You can still find out
你還可以發現啊
He Jinjia
賀金家
On some version issues related to the script
在這個跟底本相關的一些版本問題上面
This man is bold
這個人就是膽大包的天
OK how to say
OK 怎麼說呢
He not only divides this creation into spirits
他不但把這個創世紀分成化成之精
and the spirit of creation
還有造成之精
A little bit more detailed on this preference
比較細一點的這個偏好上面
He also has something different in this place
他也有一些不一樣的這個地方
OK, for example, Diamond King Jing is Liu Wang Ji
OK 比方說鑽王精就是六王紀
OK Volume 10 has a total of 26 articles
OK 第十卷總共有26篇
In fact, it is better than the Clementine version of the five elders themselves
其實比這個克萊曼特版的這個五家老本身精
one extra
多了一個
His so-called bias is actually what we call dirty now
他所謂偏其實我們現在叫髒
One more OK
多了一張 OK
That's because we built it because
那這因為我們把它造出來是因為
He Jin, there will be one shaya left
賀金那將剩一沙一雅
Chapter 38 of Leftover Essence
剩之精的第38篇
Dirty beautician for this Hazakill
這個Hazakill的髒美師
He won it to the tenth volume of this diamond king
他把它贏到這個鑽王精的第十卷
dubbed into a drill
配成一個鑽
drill articles
鑽篇
OK, but He Jinhai, he can be honest, he will tell you, this poem, I got it here from this slow place, OK, this is what I think He Jinhai, I actually don't understand how this guy is so bold, he dared to cut your Bible, OK, he dared to cut your Bible, so even if you want to find this one with his,
OK,不過賀金海呢,他也能誠實的,他就跟你說,這個詩啊,我是從這個慢慢的地方,我把它弄來這邊的,OK,這個是我覺得賀金海,我實際上搞不清楚這一個人怎麼這麼大膽,他敢割你的聖經,OK,他敢割你的聖經,所以你就算是想要去找這一個一本跟他的,
This Bible Zhang Jie, biased, biased, biased, is exactly the same as this Bible,
這個聖經張傑啊,偏輸,偏符,這個偏弄啊,是完全這個一模一樣的這個聖經啊,
I'm afraid, the first one is not easy, so what if you find the second one, OK, He Jinhai is actually very clear about why he wants to change these things, OK, so these are actually quite
恐怕啊,第一個不容易,第二個就算你找到又怎麼樣,OK,賀金海其實很清楚,知道他為什麼要變動這一些東西,OK,所以這一些其實是一些相當
First of all, we are now waiting for sex,
機首的,我們現在有待性要為止,
materials are limited
材料都很有限的一些
Some koans in the biblical conference history
聖經營議史上面的一些公案
so
所以
I see a lot of this bible to the end
我看到很多這個聖經到最後
I now at least I now say this whole
我現在至少我現在這個整個說
The last sentence
最後一句
This five-big bible in the Crano edition
這克拉諾版的這個五加大本聖經
is to solve the first problem
是解決第一本問題
as of today
到今天為止
largest common divisor
最大的這個公約數
OK
OK
This is about China National Investment Pavilion
這個關於中國國家投資館
his this
他的這個
If he didn't open the last book
上本書他不開放的話
Because all the books in Beijing are used later
因為北京的書全部都用後來
After 49 years, all rely on this
四九年之後全部都依賴這個
This area of ​​China National Investment Pavilion
中國國家投資館這一個區了
he is not open
他不開放
OK like a baby
OK當寶貝一樣
OK
OK
we will always be
我們永遠這個就
This problem will never be solved
這個問題就永遠這個沒辦法這個解開
OK
OK
itself is a public opinion
本身是一個民意
So He Jinnai in a yes indeed
所以赫金奈在一個是的確是
There are some arrangements in the Bible
有一些在聖經的安排上面
yes there are some very very surprising
是有一些非常非常令人驚訝
surprise arrangement
吃驚的安排
OK
OK
then the future
那話就未來
What I pay more attention to is He Qingtai's language problem
我比較看重的還是賀清泰語言的問題
Because this is the first vernacular
因為這是第一本的白話
our nerves
我們的神經
So when we get it, we must pay attention to
所以我們拿到它的時候注意的一定是
vernacular these two words
白話這兩個字
OK
OK
Then we say that we don't like the word
那我們說不大願意這一個字
it's a copy of this one
它是一本這一個
The so-called Mandarin Bible
所謂官話的聖經
People are because of He Qingtai
人是因為賀清泰
the text he used
他用的這個文字
actually quite
其實是相當
you are familiar
你熟的
quite familiar
相當熟悉的
you can say this
你可以這樣講
OK
OK
and it has some
而且它有一些
Very
非常
very interesting special usage
非常有趣的一些特殊的用法
Here I first demonstrate that
這裡我先示範出來的是
Before He Shengtai
在賀聖太之前呢
also which catholic masters
也有哪一些天主教主人
here's some translation of the bible
來一些聖經的這個翻譯
This one is called
這個有一個叫做
Yuen Long Nok's One
元朗諾的一個
a missionary in spain
西班牙的一個傳教士
in his 1636
他的一六三六年的時候
I wrote a book called Verses of the Bible
我義了一本書叫做聖經之節
but no
可是不是
Don't follow the subtitles
不要按照字幕上來看
OK
OK
this bible verse
這個聖經之節
The national translation of the Bible is not here
在這裡並沒有把聖經全國的翻譯出來
holy bible
聖經之節的聖經
It's three pairs of the so-called
是三對那種所謂的
bible study time
聖經之學的時候
This verse that everyone should read
大家要讀的片段的這個經文
So the book of bible verses
所以聖經之節這本書
although very thick
雖然很厚
But
可是
it
它
it only means probably
它只義了大概是
fifty three
五十三
About fifty-four weeks a year
一年大概五十四個禮拜吧
fifty three four weeks
五十三四個禮拜
Fifty-Three Four Pasagis
五十三四個Pasagis
OK
OK
nothing more
唯此而已
Then these Pasagis
然後這些Pasagis
it will add some explanation
它會加上一些解釋
this explanation
這個解釋
Then it uses the word intuition
然後它用的是直覺兩個字
But that explanation is still quite far
可是那個解釋還是相當遠的
OK
OK
Yang Maruo translates this Holy Spirit Son's Day
楊瑪若這個翻譯這個聖靈子節
was in 1639
是在1639年
Before Yang Maruo
在楊瑪若之前
Actually Ai Weiwei translated this again
其實艾維維他又翻譯了這個
The so-called incarnation of God is fierce in words and deeds
所謂天主降身言行激烈
This is a so-called gospel and technology
這是一種所謂的福音和技
In fact, this is the first book
其實這個說是有第一本的
This first book is called
這個第一本叫
Wita Christi
Wita Christi
OK
OK
Life of Christ
Life of Christ
holy son
聖靈子
sorry for the harsh comment
對不起這個激烈的聲評
OK
OK
Yang Maruo this
楊瑪若這個
I'm sorry when Ai Weiwei translated
對不起艾維維翻譯的時候
this
這個
He said he dared not speak up
他說他不敢言義
OK
OK
because
因為
that book and this
那本書這個跟
In this Holy Spirit he knew
他所認識的這個聖靈裡面
also lost this gospel
也輸了這個福音書
OK
OK
because said album
因為說的專輯
there is a little difference
是有一點差別的
So he said he dare not speak righteously
所以他說他不敢言義
In any case, he is still a text-to-text translator
不管怎麼樣,他仍然是一本文文文的翻譯
The time closest to He Jintai is Paris Foreign Mission Society
最靠近賀金太的時間是巴黎外方傳教會
A man named Bai Yusheng
一個叫白玉生的一個人
The book he translated is called "The Gospel of Facts as Unwilling"
他翻譯的一本我們簡稱叫《事實一如不願的福音合計》
This so-called fact refers to the "Master's Blessings in Books"
這個所謂的事實指的就是《師福於書》
He deleted the repetition of "Fu Yu Shu"
他把《福於書》重複的地方刪掉
Organize a non-overlapping turn of Jesus
組織出一份不會重疊的耶穌的轉機出來
This is still Chinese
這個還是文言文
only near too
只有靠近太的時間點
close too finally think
靠近太終於認為
according to him
根據他的說法
He thinks I should learn English or not
他認為我應該不應該學英文
You shouldn't learn this sutra of love without meaning
不應該學這個愛無略來意經
I have to be busy
也要忙得為呢
Because he landed from Macau
因為他從澳門這個上岸
What about after going ashore?
上岸之後呢
started contacting this one
開始接觸了這一個
Continue to learn the commissioner
繼續開始學專員啦
ok you
ok你
In fact, the contact is the book
其實接觸的就是上書
For me, the above book is the one that should be changed to
上書對我來講是那個上的應該是要改成
up in the sky
天上的上啦
ok
ok
That is to say
也就是說啊
It's a bible
是一本天書啊
i don't understand him at all
我根本看不懂他
ok
ok
gave this annotation
就給了這個註解
Sometimes I doubt it, just comment
一些時候都懷疑就註解
right?
註的對不對
ok
ok
So writing a letter is certainly not that simple.
所以上書這個當然不是那麼簡單的
a book
一本書啦
The style of the book
上書的這個style
ok actually quite
ok其實是相當相當的
difficult
不容易的
ok
ok
then this
那麼這個
this
這個
festival of sound
聲音之節
Just use this to go to the book and go to the book
就用這個上書裡面而且上書裡面
Be your good Moz body
做你的好摩茲體啊
to translate
來翻譯
ok
ok
Learn from his book The Book of Voices to be honest
學他那本聲音之節說實在的
I really doubt how many people can read it
有多少人能讀的懂,我真的很懷疑
ok, that proves that there will be a problem involved
ok,那證明裡面都會牽涉到一個問題
Normal sound pronunciation, but rarely pay attention to say
一般聲音發音,但很少會去注意說
are you right or wrong
你意對還是意錯
ok, right or wrong, originally
ok,意對意錯,本來
I should have been right
我本來就應該要意對的
ok, that's the right one
ok,那意對的這一個對
ok, actually very
ok,其實是非常
A very off track concept
非常掉軌的一個概念
ok, this is for
ok,這個對於是
In other words, this Chinese time translates the above Chinese time
或者說這個中時翻譯上面的這個中時
what should be timed with
應該中時與什麼東西
That's actually a very derailed question.
那其實是一個非常掉軌的一個問題
Let me give you an example, because I don't understand
我舉例來講好了,因為我這變不懂
I am not a bible expert
我變不是一個聖經專家
I'm not, I don't understand Hebrew
這我也不是,我也不懂 Hebrew
ok, my friend is Professor Li Zhichang from the Chinese University of Hong Kong
ok,我朋友這一個香港這個中華大學的李智長教授
I also invited him to this accountability office, this one to give a speech
也是我請他到這一個問責所,這一個來演講
and play this river river
並玩這個河河本
OK
OK
He said this when He Heben opened
他就說這個在河河本一打開的時候
Well, this god doesn't know how many days
那麼這個上帝不知道在第幾天的時候
Created a head
創造了一隻啊一頭啊
Because what we want to translate is called
因為我們要翻譯的話叫
Sea Monster
Sea Monster
OK
OK
sea ​​monster
海中的怪物
A thing like this came out of this one
這樣子的一個東西這一個出來的
right
對
God didn't invent anything
他上帝沒發明一個東西出來啊
He'll say um, that's good
他都會說嗯這是好的
OK
OK
You found out he said the monster came out and he also said um it's good
你發明他說怪物出來他也說嗯這是好的
Well
呃
did you react like that
你有這麼反應嗎
Just learned this everyone
剛學著這個人人
how to ask
要問怎麼說
Do you just follow along?
你就照著翻嗎
OK
OK
If you want to turn it according to
你要照著翻的話
I think the church will revolutionize
我看教會會革命的
OK
OK
uh no
呃不行啊
They don't dare to flip like that
那個他們也不敢這樣翻
OK
OK
uh they use this uh
呃他們就用這個呃
how to say
怎麼說啊
Uh, the tone is a bit more complete.
呃比較完一點的這個口氣
Go get this Sea Monster
去去把這個Sea Monster
The concept warms it up
這個概念把它給暖和了
so that you don't feel so strong when you read it
讓你讀起來不會感覺那麼強烈
Holy land actually created a monster
聖地居然創造了一隻怪獸
So this is the holy yin range
所以這個是聖陰範圍
In fact, the scope of Buddhism is almost the same
其實佛中範圍也差不多是一樣
often occur
常常出現的狀況
guru is guru in teaching
宗師是宗師於教義
not guru yu original text
而不是宗師於原文
Our general current concept is translation
我們一般現在的觀念是翻譯
It should be Guru Yu's original text
應該是宗師於原文才對
No way
No way
This word has never existed since
這個字無以來
Until today, the combined practice book
一直到今天合本的修練本
None of them are masters in the original text
都不是宗師於原文
all masters
都是宗師於教義
Including this big book
包括這個物家大本
while translating
瞬間在翻譯的時候
Nine clouds in Jerusalem
九雲在耶路沙冷
study at the university
大學那邊學習
learn a western
學著一個西部
while in jerusalem
在耶路沙冷的時候
bible
聖經啊
OK
OK
St. Augustine
聖奧克斯丁
Augustine
奧古斯丁啊
OK
OK
Well in Rome this one
那麼在羅馬這一個
As soon as I hear that he is translating this one, I will make an appointment.
這個一聽說他在翻譯這一個就約啊
write a letter now
馬上就趕快寫一封信
This one went to Jerusalem and gave him
這一個到耶路上去給他
what's in the letter
信裡面說什麼東西呢
The original text you are reading now
你現在在看的這一個原文
If this subtogent of our faith
如果跟我們信仰的這一個subtogent
OK
OK
This is the Greek word for
就是希臘文的這一個就約
if there is no bottom
如果說沒有底處的話
you can translate
你可以照翻譯
OK
OK
if there is a bottom
如果有底處的話
please don't translate it
請你不要翻譯出來
OK
OK
you make this one wrong
你就讓這一個錯
Let him be wrong until the end
錯就讓他一直錯到底
OK
OK
the bible is often like this
聖經常常是這樣子的
because if you don't
因為如果你不這樣子的話
I'm really going to make this
我真的會造成這個造
this this this
這個這個
education becomes this one
教育就變成這一個
there will be a minute hand
會有分針了
OK
OK
if there is a minute hand
有分針的話
That's what makes the church unrest
那就是形成教會動蕩不安
In ancient times, the west was the orthodox education system
那在古時候西方是正教育體的
church unrest
教會動蕩不安
will definitely affect
一定會影響
to the issue of politics
到政治上面的這個問題
so this is a very big question
所以這是一個非常大的一個問題
So I often say this word stock since
所以我常說這個字股以來啊
Religious translation this support is
宗教翻譯這個support is
The most should be to the original text should be the most
最應該要對原文要應該是最
The most faithful ok but
最忠實的ok可是
no way ok is often the most unfaithful
no way ok往往是最不忠實的
ok this this this
ok這個這個這個
how do you say this
這個是怎麼說
translate this
這個翻譯這個
the content of the problem
內容的這個問題啦
but because of the content
不過因為內容
Already framed by this teaching
已經被這個教義給框住了
so generally
所以一般
translating this
在翻譯這個
when the sound is actually
聲音的時候其實
What everyone pays attention to is
大家重視的是
what do i want to use
我到底要用什麼樣子的
style to translate the sound
style來翻譯這個聲音
ok then some Augustine
ok那麼 some Augustine
he wrote a book called
他寫過一本書叫
on Christian doctrine ok
on Christian doctrine ok
because at this time
因為這個時候
he christianity has not yet appeared
他基督教還沒有出現
So I dare not translate him into tenure
所以我不敢把他翻譯成了任期的
I can only translate it as this Catholicism
我只能把它翻譯成為這個念天主教義
It develops from Cicero's view the so-called free types of style
它從西塞羅的看法發展出所謂的free types of style
This style divides it into three bodies
這個style把它分成這個三體
There are so-called high-level questions
有所謂的高級問題
There are so-called intermediate problems
有所謂的中級問題
or intermediate questions
或中級問題
There are also so-called low-level problems
還有所謂的低級問題
or the so-called flat problem
或所謂的平直問題
These three styles do not actually represent
這三種style其實並不代表
Which one is good or which one is bad
就是說哪一種好或是哪一種不好
It only has the function above this function
它只有這個功能上面的作用而已
as i speak to you now
像我現在對各位講話
I can't this seems to be in
我不可能這個好像是在
The general is lecturing
將軍這個在訓話
When asking troops to fight
要求部隊要打仗的時候
I speak in a very, very high style
我用了一種非常非常高昂的那種style來講話
I can probably only use the kind of words that you can understand, which is more straightforward.
我大概只能夠用你們能夠聽得懂的那種話比較平直一點的這個話
Let's talk about the old and the new Bible
來跟各位談古新聖經
So I actually use the third kind of problem
所以我用的其實是第三種這個問題
So I just accidentally ran out sometimes
所以我剛剛有些時候不經意跑出
For example, draw something like this
比方說像這一類的畫出來
these three questions
這三種問題
The bear tail problem is of course to move
熊尾問題當然是要move
want one person
要一人
The central problem is to make people feel like making up
中央問題是要讓人覺得補起來
full of comfort and happiness
滿舒服滿快樂的
the straight question or the low level question
那平直問題或是低級問題
His purpose is to teach
他的目的是要教人
So most of us as teachers actually teach people
所以我們當老師的其實大部分教人
It's all about quality
都是這個品質問題
Although these three questions
雖然說這三種問題
Not that you are in the same article
並不是說你在同一篇文章裡面
Or in the same speech
或是說同一個speech裡面
You have always chosen a style to use
你一直選用一種這個style來用
you often know three
你常常會三種
will mix
會混著用
He Jinnai from 9M
賀錦奈他從9M那邊
The concept of that dream is
那個dream的概念是
He has to use the third question to translate the bible
他必須要用第三種問題來翻譯這個聖經
I'm hanging a new section here
我這裡掛好一個新的部分
Because the situation is a bit special
因為情況比較特殊一點
a little exception
稍微例外一點
He's bad for this little Marlowe
他不利於這個小樣馬羅
My I56 uses 5A to apply
我I56用5A的上書
parent number font
母號體揮辦
use this
用用用的這個
Use this variety show
用用用的這個綜藝
He Jinnai's emphasis on this article
賀錦奈在這條條的強調
only say this bible
只有說這個聖經
What we should pay attention to is
我們應該要看重的是
This truth in the Bible
聖經裡面的這個道理
the word find or sentence
這個詞找或是語句
In fact, God still has this blood spirit man
其實天主還有這個血精人
Actually it doesn't matter
其實都無所謂的
OK, don't take it too seriously
OK,並不必太重視
OK
OK
What is this Planes style
什麼叫做這個Planes style
What about quality issues?
所謂品質問題呢
St. Augustine's definition is
St. Augustine他下的這個定義是
The statement is relatively peaceful
語句是比較平和
more mature
比較成熟
no such premature death
沒有這種早逝
He is closer to the masses
他比較貼近這個大眾
So I said He Qingtai
所以我說賀清泰
At least when he's translating in real vernacular
至少他用真正的白話在翻譯的時候
He doesn't use Mandarin
他並不是用官話
It is translating in Beijing dialect
而是用北京的書語在翻譯
OK
OK
his translation is very
他的翻譯是非常
Sometimes this, this, this, how to say
有些時候這個這個這個怎麼說
After all, it is written exclusively for foreigners
畢竟是老外用專用寫作
OK
OK
Often some of this writes
常常有一些這個寫
there are some laws
有一些依法
is to make ourselves very stimulating
是讓我們自己非常刺激
For example
舉例來講好了
you translated that one word
你翻譯那個一個字的
OK
OK
did i make a word
我是不是有做一個字的
Then say the word war of this war
然後說這個戰爭的戰這個字好了
His usage is the same as our current usage
他的用法跟我們現在的用法
I'm afraid it's very different
恐怕很不一樣
OK
OK
Feliz
Feliz
Feliz Dunn
Feliz Dünn
This Feliz Dunn
這Feliz Dünn
Really come to fight
真來戰
OK
OK
About Abel and his parables come to fight
約亞伯同他的比喻來戰殺
Saiba
賽巴
OK
OK
I think there's a real battle here
我想這裡面這一個戰真來戰
This battle is a
這戰是一個
Is a verb that does not care to explain in English
是一個不計乎動詞用英文來解釋
OK
OK
Then let's fight Saiba
那麼來戰殺賽巴
And I used it as a verb, OK
又把它當計乎動詞這一個使用了OK
Actually we rarely use this one
實際上我們很少用這一個
this
這個
Two usages of this actually we
兩種這個用法其實我們
except dialect
除方言
OK
OK
We rarely have this in Mandarin.
我們很少這個在國語裡面啊
Think of war as an OK that counts verbs but not verbs, we are
把戰爭這一個當作計乎動詞不計乎動詞的OK我們就是
fight
作戰嘛
right
對不對
Fighting on both sides OK
兩面作戰OK
he doesn't talk like that
他不会像那样讲的
he was in that era
他在那个时代
in the former home era
在前家时代
he would say that
他会那样讲
St below
下面的圣
yes
是
Sentifly
Sentifly
Colorful
Colorite
or Dediculate
或是Dediculate
these two words
这两个字
he translates to
他都翻译成为
holy
圣
And you see a music added to the back
而且你看后面加了一个乐
In other words what is holy
换句话说圣是什么
what word
是什么词
verb
动词
San Dang verb
圣当动词
in Chinese
中文里面
I
我
in the knowledge of some
有些人的知识里面
almost never saw me
几乎是没有看过我的
saint can be a noun
圣可以当名词
can make this a new word
可以做这一个新文词
But in our usage
可是我们的用法里面
At least in the usage of Mandarin
至少国语的用法里面
It's not a proper verb
就是不当动词来用
But He Qingtai
可是贺青太
he takes him as a verb
他把他当动词
to use
来用
OK
OK
this is a very special place
這是一個非常特殊的地方
There are some words besides
下面還有一些單字之外
For example, if there are more than two characters, we call them words.
比方說兩個字以上我們就叫詞了啦
OK
OK
Some of the applications used in ancient and modern times
古今申請用到的一些
some of the more common words
這個比較常用的一些詞
I put the Guina out for example
我把貴納出來比方說
the total one
總共的那個
total of this word
總共這一個字
This word is our current way of speaking
這一個字是我們現在的講法
Mr. He's teaching is of common species
賀先生的講法是共種
just heard
剛好聽到過來
OK
OK
I'm going to check Honglianmeng
我去查紅蓮夢
I just found out
我才發覺
Mr. He did not make a mistake
賀先生他並沒有用錯
Red lotus dream is full of co-species
紅蓮夢裡面都是共種
OK
OK
So he did nothing wrong
所以他沒有用錯
What about the snake?
蛇呢
Snake is what we say in Taiwan now
蛇是我們現在在台灣的講法
What about Hebei people?
問河北人呢
To this day, people in Hebei still hold a
到今天為止河北人都還把著一個
snake called snake
蛇叫蛇蟲
Let's say again that I have an old minister from Hebei.
我們再說我有河北老相的話
maybe you will understand
或許您會了解
OK
OK
That
那
help
幫忙呢
they are quite
他們就相當
OK quite
OK 相當
Of course I also feel
我當然也覺得說
Are you so wrong
你是不是這個超錯了
OK
OK
So luckily there's a lot of this now
所以還好現在有很多這個
Novel
小說啊
This one has electronic boards to search
這一個有電子板可以search
OK
OK
I look down
我一看下去
Wow
哇
I have no knowledge myself
我自己沒有知識
not to come in without knowledge
不是要進來沒有知識
is quite right
是相當沒有錯
OK
OK
I'm pretty inside
我裡面相當
one year
一年
when you want to help
要講幫忙的時候
it's almost
它幾乎
Almost all of this uses the word quite
幾乎這個全用著一個相當這個字
There's this coolness in there
那裡面有這個內爽
This was originally from the book
這本來是從上書裡面出來的
OK
OK
Kakindai
賀金台
it also uses
它也用
OK
OK
Since it came out of the book
那既然從上書裡面出來
Actually it doesn't necessarily mean
其實也不一定就是說
This non-profit
這一個非利
This Beijinger will only use this one
這個北京人這一個才會用啦
I don't know if people in other places will use it
我搞不好別的地方的人也會用啦
OK
OK
Then this will actually be something we won't talk about.
那這個實際上也會是我們就不談了
Then if this is taken as
那如果這個當做
most people in the world
世間時的大部分的人
It's back to the previous page.
是在回到前面一頁好了
Tinnitus Heroes
是耳鳴英雄傳
or Red European Dream
或是紅歐夢
The writing time of Hongoumeng
紅歐夢寫作的時間
In fact, it was the pre-agricultural era
其實就是前農時代
The biography of Wenkang's tinnitus heroes is more difficult to say
文康耳鳴英雄傳是比較難說
Some people deduce him to these tariffs
有人把他推論到這些關稅
Someone said to go to Daoguang
有人說要到道光
but no matter what
不過不管怎麼樣
Many scholars believe
很多學者都認為
Tinnitus Heroes should represent
耳鳴英雄傳所代表的應該是
Probably from Qiannong to Daoguang
大概是前農一直到道光
This is about a hundred years or so
這大概將近一百年左右的
Beijing dialect in Beijing
北京的北京話
OK
OK
So I had to choose these novels
所以我只好這一些小說
To do well is a litmus test
來做好像是一個試金石
Check out this gold belt
來看看這個賀金帶
used some weird words
用了一些奇奇怪怪的語句
is it right or wrong
到底是對還是錯
it made me realize
這讓我發覺
he did use it
他的確是用過了
OK, in other words, these words, in a sense, they should be some words commonly used by ordinary people in Beijing in this century
OK,換句話說,這一些話呢,某一意義上來講,它應該是北京比較這一個世紀小民常用的一些話
OK, let's see the next one
OK,我們看下一張好了
From this point of view, we can all say that when He Xingnai is translating, he prefers to use the so-called planning strategy.
這個從這個角度來看,我們大家可以說,賀興奈這個翻譯的時候,他是比較喜歡用所謂的規劃的這一個策略
OK, this English is called domestication
OK,這英文叫做domestication
Planning means to follow the Chinese teaching method
規劃的意思是說,跟著中國人的講法走
OK, but, sometimes this planning is really too planned
OK,可是呢,有些時候這個規劃實在是規劃的太過分了
OK, some people like their special panis, this pie
OK,有的人喜歡他們特殊的這個panis,這個餅
OK, IOR was in the birth of God, Yanqing fierce, in the early seventeenth century
OK,IOR在天主降生,燕青激烈,在十七世紀初期的時候
OK, he is taking this disease, this disease is a layer of disease
OK,他是把這個病,這個病就一層病啦
The whole Panis is sick, because it is still called sick, right?
整個Panis就一層病,因為都還叫病,對不對?
OK, but what about He Jintai, he, super planned
OK,可是賀金泰呢,他呢,超級規劃的
OK, he called it Mantou
OK,他把它叫饅頭
Ah, what about steamed buns? If you talk about this, he will continue to localize it.
啊,那饅頭呢,如果說這個,他繼續這個本土化下去啊
He just called him Bobo, OK
他乾脆就把他叫薄薄了,OK
So he has several kinds of this, this epidemic method, in fact, they are all similar to steamed buns
所以他有好幾種這個,這個疫法,其實都跟饅頭差不多的
OK, what about the ranan pancake that we now make?
OK,那我們現在人家做這一個薄餅的蘭乾啊,這一種東西呢
He simply put a layer of pancake, I don't know if pancake has words, OK
他乾脆把他一層薄餅,我不知道薄餅有沒有字嘛,OK
Then he was originally this, this, this, this, this, this so-called Cruce Do, this
那他本來是這個,這個這個包餅的,這個,這個所謂的Cruce Do,這個
the word
這個字
It means flat
它意義的好像是扁
it is flat and thin
它是扁薄薄
I really don't know what a flat thin thing is
我實在搞不清楚扁薄薄是什麼東西
Everyone should be more flat-faced steamed buns.
大家還是比較有扁力點的饅頭吧
so you're inside the last supper
所以你在最後的晚餐裡面
jesus said
耶穌說
Jesus broke the cake
耶穌破開這個餅
Then give his picture say this
然後給他的圖這樣說
This is my body
This is my body
this is my body
這是我的身體
What about this paragraph?
這一段呢
He Jindai wrote it like this
賀金帶是這樣寫的
Jesus surrendered to this steamed bun
耶穌降伏給這個饅頭
Then what
然後呢
Divide the buns into pieces
把饅頭分成塊
good at this his steamed bun
善於這個他的饅頭
OK
OK
where is jesus
耶穌呢
he himself
他自己
Metaphor yourself as a business
比喻自己是生意這兩
these two
這兩
Doesn't he have Ling Wangtang?
他不是有令王堂嗎
isn't it
不是嗎
OK
OK
Gu Xin's voice
顧心聲音
Translate the words of Jesus
把耶穌這一句話譯成是
I am a steamed bun of business
我是生意的饅頭
OK
OK
i don't know this
我不知道這個
How did Beijingers sound at that time?
當時的北京人聽起來怎麼樣了
but today we
但是我們今天
Woke up today feeling weird
今天起来是觉得很怪怪的
that's even weirder
那更怪的事
this hunting king
这个猎王纪
on this one
这一个上
originally a word called
本来是一句话叫做
charcoal baked pancakes
炭火烤熟的饼
OK
OK
He Tiannai in his kings gold
贺天奈在他的众王金
Hunting King Ji, his name is Zhongwangjin
猎王纪他叫做众王金
It is said to be a steamed bun of a living dragon and mouse
说是活龙龙老鼠的一个馒头
I can't cook though
我虽然不会做饭
can't cook
不会做菜
But I know that steamed buns are steamed
可是我知道馒头是用蒸的
He said steamed buns belong to mice
他说馒头是老鼠的
We also know that this duck's he went
我们也知道这个鸭的他去了
he has many of these
他有很多这一类的
This kind of over-planning
规划得太过分的这种
this sentence
这种句子
find it very interesting
觉得非常有趣
Let's look at the next page
我们再看下一页
OK
OK
Another place to plan is
那另外一个规划的地方是
this
这个
He Tiannai said that Tiandao
贺天奈说那天天刀
The physics museum in this origin
这个渊源渊里面的物理馆
go paint
去画画好了
OK
OK
in other words
換句話說
Qing Palace
清宮啊
he actually
他其實
not angry
不群怒
he is not good
他不妙聲的
The language of the Qing court
清宮的語言他
he is very familiar
他很熟的
So inside the ancient and modern holy palace
所以古今聖宮裡面
There is a Thai
有個泰人
or the dynasty of the egyptians
或是埃及人的王朝
also often think
也常常認為
some in here
在這裡面的一些
Up and down relationship
上下的關系
so
所以
a Guo Wang
一個郭王
or within a family
或是一個家族裡面
richer family
比較有錢的家族
you see this one
你們看到這一個
He Jin people will put the family
賀金人會把這一個家族裡面
this special character
這一個專門的人物
called master
就叫做主子
Those who do things for him are called slaves
幫他做事的人就叫奴才
OK
OK
Then what
然後呢
master of course
主子當然
Of course the slave must follow the master
奴才當然要跟這個主子
This is commonly known as auspicious
這個俗稱吉祥
OK
OK
I have to say hello to him too
也必須要跟他請安
so these words
所以這一些話
you can see that
這你可以看出來
that is
就是說
He Jin gave birth to a new year's home
賀金人生了一個公年掛家
Then his place is indeed
那麼他的一地的確確實
also received a public year
也受到了一個公年
Can't keep up with the impact
跟不上這個影響
Not only this effect
不只這個影響
There is also the following effect
還有下面一個影響
we can take a look
我們可以看一下
not a good question
不是很好問題
there is another
另外還有一個
not this
不是這
no and not this
不是也不是這
Just wait until you can't find it
等下找不到就算了
we now find
我們現在找到
let me talk
我說再說吧
ok
ok
anyway
anyway
his
他的
his translation strategy
他的這個翻譯策略
basically
基本上
if he can internalize
是他如果能夠內化
or planning
或規劃
he can plan
他就可以規劃
What I was actually looking for was a
我其實剛剛想要找的是一個
so-called prison
所謂的一個監圈
we just know
我們就知道
Our green stuff, this growth pack
我們這青東西這個一個增長裝
see too much
看太多了
we know what this is
我們就知道這個什麼
what diameter
什麼圈徑
Circle diameter is a term that is often heard
圈徑是常常聽到的一個名詞
In fact, circle diameter is a character of Qingcha
其實圈徑是清查的一個形字
There are also various ways of the circle diameter
圈徑還有各種不同的這個圈徑的方式
ok
ok
if it is
那如果是
There is a circle of people
有一種叫人圈
ok
ok
Foretell this and employ this
預說這個用人這個
you can go no problem
你可以走沒問題
a little house arrest
有點形容軟禁
next to you is a lot of water
你旁邊是一大堆的水中
stand over there
站那邊
But this line is to monitor you
可是這一線是監視你的
ok
ok
this circle of people
這個叫人圈
Then there is also this, use strong and low to get angry
那也有這個用強低這個氣起來
you ride in it
你就搭在裡面
you are not allowed to run around
你不准亂跑
ok
ok
some are locked in matter
有些是關在物質裡面
you can't run around
你不能亂跑
General Su Liyuan seems to be
這個蘇利元將軍好像
experienced these things
就經歷過這些東西
so what
所以呢
From this Chinese form, he
他從這個中國形制裡面
he created himself
他自己去創造出
egyptians in
埃及人在
sorry
對不起
some people in egypt this
有的人在埃及這個
quilt
被
what
幹嘛
means being forced to do something
就是說被迫去做一些
when writing some projects
去寫一些工程的時候
He invented this engineering circle
他就發明了這一個工程圈
ok
ok
that pair of gold
那對金
prison circle
一事的時候就發明了監圈
He is buying now
他是現買現買啦
OK came across these in China
OK在中國碰到這些
this lecture
這個講法
Just translate it like this
乾脆就這樣翻譯下去了
OK
OK
Well
呃
How to say
怎麼說
Although this is a
這雖然說是一種
this one
這一個
Well
呃
Um
嗯
Compare
比較
close to this China
貼近這一個中國
A kind of
今天在貼近中國的一種
translation method
翻譯方法
However, this translation method is already a language
不過這種翻譯方法已經是把語言啊
Well
呃
It's not just translating this language anymore.
已經不僅是在翻譯這一個語言了啦
He is also translating culture
他也是在翻譯文化啦
OK
OK
Well
呃
so i say
所以我說
in here
這裡面啊
Well
呃
cusine bible this one
古辛聖經這一個
this
這個
when he is thinking
當他在思考
He Jinnai is thinking about this one
賀金奈在思考這一個
how to translate when
要怎麼樣翻譯的時候
in fact already
事實上已經
total
總
already already
已經已經
is doing a
在做的是一種
Well
呃
this one of culture
文化的這一個
Transferred this question
轉移的這一個問題了
OK
OK
what about this question
那這個問題呢
If this cultural transfer across state lines
如果是跨州的這種文化轉移
Actually
其實是
is what we call modernity today
是我們今天所謂現代性的
this ring
其中的這一環
OK
OK
I dare not say this ancient and modern scripture
我不敢說這個古今生經
How closely related to what we call modernity
跟我們所謂的現代性有多密切的關係
But at least I invented a term called
但是至少我發明一個名詞叫做
dad called
爸爸叫做
bottom
最下面
Chen Feng's modernity in what he often said
陳峰在常說的內容裡面的現代性
i think it should be ok
我想應該可以吧
OK
OK
I haven't written anything yet
我還沒寫到什麼話
I spoke
我講了
We have probably already talked about this bandon
這個bandon我們大概已經講過了
i think i keep talking
我想我一直談
because it's almost time
因為時間也差不多了
I have been talking about a He Jintai
我一直談著一個賀金太
This ancient and modern scripture
這一本古今生經
I once did a study
我曾經做過一個研究
is one this one clear one
是一個這一個清楚的一個
Missionaries called Marlowe
傳教士叫做馬洛社
a novel he wrote
他寫的一篇小說
OK
OK
He based this on Cicero's
他根據這個西塞羅的這個
The Republic
The Republic
OK
OK
That Skipio on the last side
最後一面的那個Skipio
His housewife took him to heaven
他主婦帶他到天上去
Then look around the universe from the sky and see the earth
然後從天上環視宇宙看到地球
An imagination of Cicero like this
這樣子的一個西塞羅的一個想像
This vision of Joseph Marosell visiting Cicero
馬若瑟曾經訪西塞羅的這個想像
wrote a novel
寫了一篇小說
I haven't read this novel.
這篇小說我沒有看過這一個刻本
I only see superbooks
我只看到超本
i have a day
我有一天
once i wrote an article
有一次我寫了一篇文章
when reading at a meeting
在會議上讀的時候
someone asked me
就有人問我說
What's the point of your research on superbooks
你研究超本有什麼意義
This means that
意思是說
Superbook is just a person
超本也不過就是一個人
copy a book
把某一本書拿來抄
It does not mean that the book had a great influence
並不意義說這本書有很大的影響力
What is the point of your research on this ultrabook?
你研究這個超本到底意義在哪裡
OK
OK
I know your key is the so-called influence
我知道你關鍵是所謂的影響力
this question
這一個問題
That Marlowe is another question
那馬洛瑟是另外一個問題
actually
馬洛瑟其實
That question is a big one
那個問題一個大的很
OK Maloser affected financial love
OK 馬洛瑟影響了財力愛
OK
OK
Superbook not engraved things
超本沒有刻出來的東西
For later Maloser was a Catholic missionary
對於後來馬洛瑟是天主教傳教士
But what?
可是呢
But this one he wrote
可是他寫的這一個
This one is not engraved
沒有刻出來的這一個
dream no soil skills
夢沒土技
It's a dream of heaven, a dream of heaven
就是夢天堂 夢到天堂
OK
OK
Meng did not have soil skills, but it affected the later Protestantism
夢沒土技卻影響到後來新教的
Guo Shili
比方說國石利
OK
OK
let's say this one
比方說這一個
this one milian
這一個米蓮
some of their missionary novels
他們的那一些傳教士小說
OK
OK
that's full
那是滿
a terrible thing
滿可怕的一件事情
OK
OK
What about He Qingtai?
這個賀清泰呢
He Qingtai This Old and New Bible
賀清泰這本古新聖經
same
同樣
he is still
他還是
The first trainer is not allowed to take a tick
第一個教練不准拿刻
he does not
他不
Don't mess around
不能隨便亂科的
ok
ok
The coach doesn't allow Kona to count.
教練不準科那是算的嘛
The coach is not allowed
教練不準科
The coach has nothing to show others
教練沒有所不拿給別人看
ok
ok
So around the year 181,000
所以大概是在181000年的時候啊
Just a little bit more relaxed Catholicism
就比較悠心一點的天主教
catholic or catholic room
天主教徒還是天主教室
ok
ok
just take this
就把這個
He Jintai's ancient nerve
賀金太的古形神經啊
The part of the welfare book inside.
裡面的福利書這一部分的東西啊
ok
ok
take it to guangzhou
帶到廣州去
show this one
秀給這一個
The first Protestant missionary to China
第一個來華的新教的傳教士
Robert Morrison
Robert Morrison
ok Morrison
ok Morrison
So Morrison was
那所以Morrison是曾經
read this one
讀過這一個
Well
呃
this one
這一個
archaic nerve
古形神經
at least he read
至少他讀過
welfare book ok
福利書的 ok
but i feel like
可是我感覺是
I'm afraid it's not just the welfare book
恐怕不只福利書
Morrison's category of reading
Morrison這個閱讀的範疇
I'm afraid it's pretty big ok
恐怕還蠻大的 ok
A bible later said to be the first master translation in China
一本后称是中国第一部的主本翻译的圣经
so-called holy book
所谓神天圣书
In fact, a large part of it was influenced by He Jingtai
其实有很大一部分是受到贺经台的影响
If you have read the sacred book
如果你读过神天圣书的话
The holy book is really read
神天圣书真的是读起来
You will feel that the whole O mouth has reached the extreme
你会觉得整支O口到了极点
That kind of O mouth is actually related to He Jingtai
那种O口其实是跟贺经台
I think I learned it from He Jingtai
我觉得是跟贺经台学来的
Yihe Jingtai's wish is indeed not as plain as its old counterparts
以贺经台的心愿的确是没有它的旧位异的那么白话
The old dissimilarity is vernacular
旧位异是白话的不得了
First, because of the various divine and holy books I just mentioned
先因我刚刚说过的各种不同的神天圣书
Their education level is related
他们教育程度有关系
So there are various problems that manifest
所以有各种不同的问题的展现
where to choose from time to time
哪里选择好时不时
Just to learn the kind of words that are more awkward
刚好去学到那些比较O口的那种话
so where to choose this one
所以哪里选择这一个
Well...
呃...
The god has lost
這個神明陷輸了
uh... or so-called psychological lost
呃...或是所謂的心理遭輸了
The rescue was lost, etc.
救命遭輸了等等之類的
uh...actually
呃...其實是
uh...been through this one
呃...受過這一個
and mentality of this one influence
和心態的這一個影響
even with charitable intentions
甚至與慈善意願
he's been affected
他的受過影響
It means that we are actually
等於說我們今天其實
We actually have two postures in Paradise today
我們今天其實樂園兩個姿勢
catchy
朗朗上口啦
When I was a child there was another called
我小時候還有一種叫
Cigarettes of Heart Paradise
心樂園的香煙啦
But it's not easy for everyone to see
但大家不大容易看到
Uh... if you have this mentality
呃...這個心態要有的話
Must be... antique
一定...變古董啦
must be very valuable
一定很值錢
then...we...
那...我們...
What about the two poses of Paradise?
樂園這兩個姿勢呢
not from china
並非中國故有
Only Buddhism can use it
只有佛教這一個才會用到
The two poses of Paradise
樂園這兩個姿
Is there a paradise in China
中國故有沒有樂園
if you look for it in the world
你在世間裡面找的話
That's Leto
那叫樂圖
Tu Yang's picture
圖養的圖
Letu
樂圖
inside to get involved
在裡面去連累出來的
I don't know
I don't know
But he is indeed the whole of Christianity
但是他的確是整個基督宗教
That is to say, including Catholicism and Protestantism
就是說包括天主教跟這個新教
Christianity
基督教
OK
OK
the whole of christianity
整個基督宗教
Maybe there is a Nestorian in it
搞不好還包括著一個景教在裡面
OK
OK
First
第一個
this says
這個說
Said that now I want to live in Paradise
說當下我要住在樂園
this place
這個地方
he is the first
他是第一人
OK
OK
Later, the name has been handed down like this.
後來這個名詞就這麼一直傳下來了
Inside Mirror is in when writing his Huayun dictionary
裡面Mirror is in在寫他的這個華運字典的時候
He also got up with him
他也跟他樂園起來了
Puridice is also translated as this paradise
Puridice也翻譯成為這個樂園
Clean it up
Puridiso
Puridiso is
Puridiso是
Puridion
Puridion
OK
OK
The word "paradise" is true
這個樂園這兩個字說實在的
Yang Tianyu's earliest time
楊天宇最早的時候
In fact, he dare not translate
其實他不敢翻譯了
OK
OK
he called it this
他把它叫做這個
Yang Tianyu ran to
楊天宇跑到
go down
下去
Um
嗯
maximum
最大
You don't need to find it, it's okay
不用你找到,沒關係
anyway, yang tingting is paradise
anyway,楊亭亭是樂園
paradise, paradise
paradise, paradise
ok , he uses this
ok,他是用這個
Bala Tisha or something
巴拉底少還是什麼東西之類的
transliteration
音譯的方式來翻譯
Because he believes that in Chinese culture
因為他認為中國文化裡面
Not Christianity, Catholicism
並沒有基督教、天主教
this concept of this paradise
這種樂園的這個概念
So, the transliteration transliterated
所以,音譯音譯了
ok, transliterated
ok,音譯了啦
The later Catholicism is the knowledge of Paradise
後來的天主教是對樂園這個知識
There are many ways to say this
有很多的這個講法啦
ok because later on for example
ok,因為後來比方說
In this deep area of ​​calm
在淡定的這個深區裡面
In fact, Paradise is divided into
其實樂園是分成
heavenly paradise with
heavenly paradise跟
earthly paradise
earthly paradise,地上樂園
And City Paradise
還有城市樂園
Paradise on earth is of course biting the present
地上樂園當然是咬當下
Yidian Park
他們組的一電園
Paradise
天上樂園
That's the place for the Shangdi Group.
那就是商地組的這個地方啦
ok then they
ok,那麼他們
It is derived from this book in China
就從中國這個書籍裡面連累出
For example, the saying of heaven
比方說這個天堂說法
OK
OK
So
那麼
It's all this paradise on earth
都是地上這個樂園
this trouble
這麻煩
Yang Tianyu called him
楊天宇是把他叫做
sorry heaven paradise he still calls him
對不起天上樂園他還是把他叫做
Araiso
阿拉伊索
OK
OK
earliest time
最早的時候
Luo Mingjian fought with Lima when they were in the 1580s
羅明堅跟利馬鬥他們在1580年代的時候
Bring Paradise
把樂園
Paradise on earth
地上樂園
OK
OK
this
這個
Pavaiso
帕瓦伊索
Terry
Terry
OK
OK
he moved him into
他把他移成
buddhist country
佛國
OK
OK
Buddha
佛
Buddha's country
佛祖的這個國家
OK
OK
I tell you
我跟你講
This is because your first time
這個是因為你第一次
cultural first encounter
文化上第一次碰到
when this is a new noun
這個一個新的名詞的時候
You do have so many
你的確是會有這麼多的
so big
這麼大的
this
這個
that kind of words
那種語詞
the kind of struggle above
上面的那種奮鬥
how to translate
到底要怎麼樣翻譯
You're really pretty good at finding out
你真的還蠻能夠找出
an appropriate translation
一個恰當的翻譯出來
Naga Jinna is great
那賀金奈很厲害
He calls a certain language a paradise
他這個把一定語言就叫做樂園了
Paradise down
樂園下去
Well, Xinjiao also went down with Paradise.
好了心教也跟著樂園下去了
Old teaching needless to say
舊教不用說
Plaster of the Old Church itself has been
舊教的石膏本身經
must be paradise
一定是樂園的
Heart Teaching from Morrison
心教從Morrison
From Morrison to this Guslev
從Morrison到這個Guslev
It is the so-called national stone power statement
就是所謂的國石力言
wait these people are paradise
等等這些人一律樂園
Paradise to our heart Paradise
一直樂園到我們的心樂園
still in Paradise
都還繼續在樂園
So if you want to look at it from the words
所以你如果要從語詞上面來看
this ancient and modern bible
這個古今聖經
marison may not have read it from cover to cover
馬里遜可能沒有從頭讀到尾
But also affected to some extent
可是也受到某種程度的影響
This can be seen
這個是可以看出來的
I don't have that much time
我是沒有那麼多的時間
Or one of my two essences is looking at each other
或者我兩個本質這一個互相在那邊對照著看
I think it should be possible to say something more interesting
我想應該還可以講出這個更多有趣的這個話出來的
OK
OK
Then let me talk about style at the end
那最後我談一下style好了
This style is OK
這個style OK
There is a very important scholar in the West
這個西方有一個非常重要的學者
Called Erik Albach
叫Erik Albach
He said
他說
The more vulgar language in it
裡面這個比較粗俗一點的語言
more vulgar language
比較俗氣一點的語言
to write
來寫作
doesn't mean you can't
並不意味說你不能夠從
In this rather vulgar concept
這個比較俗氣一點的概念裡面
in this language to create some kind of
這個語言裡面來創造出某種
sublime
sublime
OK
OK
A feeling like spinning tail
旋尾這樣子的一種感覺
Spin Tail is a Westerner
旋尾是西方人
the most beautiful
美最高的
extreme word
極字
OK
OK
Well
呃
I'll be full of an explanation chest
我會滿著一個解釋胸胃
words to explain
要解釋的話
i need this
我需要這個
another hour
另外一個鐘頭的時間
OK
OK
Well
呃
i can only say
我只能夠說
From the two examples I quote below
從下面我引出來的兩個例子
OK
OK
is using a very simple
是用著一個非常簡單的
This one is written in Chinese and this one
這一個中文這一個寫的
OK
OK
But what?
可是呢
here you read
這裡面你讀起來
especially if you have to follow
尤其如果你要跟
If there are words above and below
有上文有下文的話
you read
你讀起來
Your feeling is the feeling of chest and stomach
你的感覺是胸胃的感覺
OK
OK
Well
呃
first example
第一個例子啊
This is the third entry from Chinese
是這個從中文進第3篇
Well
呃
inside this
裡面這個
this came out
這個出來的
talking about
談的是
Well
呃
Alias' question
Alias的這個問題啦
OK
OK
Well
呃
at that time this
那個時候這個
this god this
這個天主這個
Hear the prophet Alias
聽到Alias這個先知啊
this one is a bit
這一個有點
when feeling discouraged
灰心的感覺的時候
god this one
天主這一個
he out
他出
he is coming
他要出現了
he appeared
他顯現了
OK
OK
in the bible
聖經裡面啊
Well
呃
sorry
對不起
This He Jin Dali medical method is a burst of landslides and seas after the appearance of God
這個賀金大理醫法是天主出現之後一陣山崩海裂
strong wind and rain
強風之雨襲來
Then God is not in the wind
然後天主不在這風內
After this storm
這風後地動
It's the same as our list
跟我們名單語是一樣的
That's right
就對當了
God is not in this cave
天主也不在這洞內
but then fire
但後是火
God is still not in this fire
天主還是不在這火內
I added a word for him
我幫他加了一個字
the day after the fire
火後天
Correction
習正
sound of gentle wind
溫和風的聲音
there is not a word in it
這裡面沒有一個字
this is the kind
這個是那種
the kind in the article
篇文裡面的那種
Very high injury point Ya sooner or later
非常高傷的點雅的遲早
But the feeling of God you read
可是你讀出來的天主的感覺
is a rather sublime feeling
是一個相當崇高的感覺
very serious
非常嚴肅
very dangerous sense of god
非常危險的天主的感覺
OK, so the following example is
OK,那下面這一個例子是
It's Epsalom, which is very famous for this
是Epsalom,這非常出名的這個
this son of david
David的這個兒子
Because he felt that this David would not pass the throne to him
他因為覺得這個David好像不會把王位傳給他
So he rebelled
所以他就起兵造反
Rebellion wins and loses
造反本來贏,後來輸
When I lost, I was chased by David
輸的時候就被David的追兵
run after
追著跑
Then Epsalom at the end
那麼Epsalom到最後的時候
Epsalom rides this lol all by himself
Epsalom自己一個人騎著這一個羅子
OK, he suddenly met David's soldier
OK,他忽然遇見David的兵
Then this Luo Zi passed through Qiu Yi
然後這個羅子穿過仇義
under the tree
欲晚樹底下
His hair got caught by a tree... a branch
他的頭髮被樹...樹枝給刮住了
The one who rides Luozi is wrong
騎著羅子那隻寫錯了
OK, I'll pin it up and run ahead
OK,我把它釘上來,往前跑
Then, He Junnai translated a sentence
然後呢,何俊奈這一個翻譯出一句
In fact, this text is not so clever
其實不是多高明的這個文字
but read it
可是讀起來
The Epsilon
這個Epsilon
that imagery becomes very large
的那一種意象變得非常龐然
he said his body
他說他的身體
hanging between heaven and earth
掛在天地之間
ok
ok
While reading this I suddenly remembered this
讀到這裡的時候我突然想起這個
such a legal
這樣子的一個依法
translation is a kind of interpretation
翻譯其實是一種詮釋
ok such a legal
ok 這樣子的一個依法
In fact, the unfilial son of Epsilon has been
其實已經把Epsilon這個不孝子
translate it as if that
把它譯成好像是那個
how to say
怎麼說啊
You don't bow your head like God
您使也不像上帝低頭的
There is no such thing as Shadan
沒有頓比下的那個沙丹
ok
ok
The imagery is very, very mammoth
這個意象是非常非常龐然的
Then we see that there is nothing great in it
那我們看到這裡面並沒有什麼偉大的
this one word this one appears
這一個字眼這一個出現
so
所以
this Obach
這個Obach
he will say ok
他才會說 ok
even if
即使是
belong
屬於
Nic on the third level question
Nic就第三級的問題
ok
ok
You can actually create the feeling of the first episode too
你其實也可以創造出第一集的感覺出來
It's Xuan Wei's feeling
就是宣偉的感覺出來
I give myself these two examples
我自己舉這兩個例子
I don't think I will mention the others
其他的我想我就不舉了
Finally, I will report to you again
最後我跟各位再報告一下
I have just reported Protestantism
我剛剛已經報告過新教
Protestantism influenced by the Old and New Bibles
新教的收到古新聖經的影響
Old teaching bibles until the 1960s one night
舊教的聖經一直到1960年代才一晚
Although they already cared about it in pre-Canadian times
雖然前加時代他們就已經在意了
But after this ban and so on
可是經過這個禁教等等之類的
They have to be ordered by the Pope to translate
他們又非得教皇這個下令才能夠翻譯
So the old school did not finish the translation until the 1960s
所以舊教到了1960年代他們才翻譯完
Everyone has followed the translated old teaching
翻譯完的舊教大家都遵循了
This Chinese version we call Shi Gaoben
這個中文本我們叫做詩高本
The author of the Poetry Gaoben is a
詩高本的詩作用者是一個
a french italian
一個法國義大利
I'm sorry, the priest of the Italian Accounting Society is called Lei Yongming
對不起義大利方計會的神父叫雷永明
OK
OK
Father Lei Yongming
這雷永明神父
italian
這義大利人
When he decided to start translating the bible for employment
他決定要開始翻譯這個聖經就業的時候
sorry when the whole bible
對不起 聖經整本的時候
He is very good with a camera
他是帶著一個攝影非常好的
a friend
一個朋友
OK
OK
camera at that time
那個時候的攝影機
Probably a huge camera
大概是很龐大的那種攝影機
he ran to
他跑到
Not long after the end of the Anti-Japanese War
他在抗戰這一鋼結束沒多久
He ran to Beitang in Beijing
他跑到北京的北塘去
OK
OK
What are you doing in Beitang?
跑到北塘幹嘛
He took He Qingtai's manuscript
他把賀青太的這個稿子
take it all out
全部都拿出來
it took a whole month
花了一整整個月的時間
they used their
他們用他們當時那種
It must be a very bulky camera
應該是很笨重的攝影機
Kacha Kacha cards one by one
卡叉卡叉的一張一張的牌
Finally shoot it
最後拍起來啊
And bite it to this side
還把它叮成這個側
This ding on one side
一側一側的這個叮
Ding Thirty Sides
叮了三十大側
Then Liu Yongming put the thirty side
然後劉永明把這三十大側
take him to live longer
再帶到他住多的
That is to say, go inside his church
也就是說他的教堂裡面去
because he wants to translate nerve
因為他要翻譯神經
nerves he can drink in for reference
他能喝進來的神經來參考
so if you read
所以如果你讀
You read the words of this ancient and modern nerve that you drink in
你讀這個喝進來的這個古今神經的話
You will find that the world knows each other
你會發覺世城相識
Because Liu Yongming has too many nouns
因為劉永明有太多名詞
They are all citing this ancient and modern nerve of drinking Qingtai
都是引用這個喝清台的這個古今神經
So this nerve that has not been officially published
所以一本沒有被正式published的這個神經
it's not without impact
它不是沒有影響的
it has a lot of influence
它影響力可大了
Both the Heart Teaching and the Old Teaching both influence
心教舊教兩教通通影響
For those of us who are generally non-religious
對於我們一般不信教的人來講
We also often hang some, such as saints
我們也常常掛著一些 比如說聖徒
These names, the names on these religions
這些名稱啊 這些宗教上面的名稱
etc
等等之類的
I still want to tell you
我還是要跟各位講
What about these nouns?
這些名詞呢 合進來方面的
OK
OK
Then because of this one of the old and new religions
然後因為新舊兩教的這一個
especially Protestant
尤其是新教
Uh, use the past
呃 延用過去
OK and then it becomes as if
OK 然後就仿佛變成
S-A-I-N-T
S-A-I-N-T
Sent
Sent
as if it becomes
仿佛就變成
uh bible uh sorry
呃 聖經 呃 對不起
There is a fixed one in the dictionary
字典裡面 固定了一個
One way to explain it is
一個 一個 一個解釋的方法就是
S-A-I-N-T
S-A-I-N-T
saint
聖徒
OK it becomes like this
OK 就變成這樣子
OK
OK
uh i spend a lot of time
呃 我花很多時間
uh 150
呃 150
This one of 1.5 million words
150 萬個字的這一個
uh this one this one
呃 這一 個 這一 個
Such a big book OK
那麼大的一本書 OK
uh i see
呃 我看
uh gave this one for 150 days
呃 給了150天這一個
Maybe I'm just talking about this one
搞不好這一個還才講
able to speak
還講得能夠
be clearer
比較清楚一點
OK so today
OK 所以今天
uh actually
呃 其實
obviously keep one
明明要留著一個
uh talk a little bit
呃 講了一些
I just hope this one is right
我 我只希望這一個對
everybody this one
大家這一個
Whether it is language history or
不管是語言史也好
OK Shenjing translation is also good
OK 深經翻譯也好
OK even linguistics
OK 甚至語言學
OK
OK
Let alone this comparative literature
那更不要說這一個比較文學
Or in terms of teaching
或者說中教學這方面
The contribution of this book is actually quite large.
這本書的貢獻其實是蠻大的
It is very worthwhile for us to study
是非常值得我們去研究的
ok thank you all
好 謝謝大家
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you Professor Li Shixue
謝謝李士學教授
we'll take ten minutes
我們就十分鐘
So there are probably only three or four questions
所以大概只有三四個問題
keep it short please
簡短一點 請
Thank you Professor Li for your wonderful speech
謝謝李教授精彩的演講
what i want to ask is
我想請教的是
a little bit of me
有一點我
Of course I understand the content
當然內容我就了解的話
i have a doubt
我有一個疑點
That is to say, he was in Beijing
就是說他當時在北京
I believe he should be able to see
我相信他應該可以看到
For the first time, most people can't read
第一次大部分人其實看不懂字
The second time I'm sure he'll notice too
第二次我相信他應該也會注意到
In fact, the life of ordinary people
其實一般人的生活
Although the Forty-Five Classics are written in classical Chinese
四十五經雖然是文言文
but everyone will
但是大家都會
can also read and sing
也會念也會唱
even
甚至
Another one is to say
再一個就是說
Even if you are a small person with four classics
即使是四經小民
at formal gatherings
在正式聚會場合
Classical Chinese is often used
常常還是會用到文言文
Then he observed these conditions
那他觀察到這些狀況
why did you decide to say
為什麼還會決定說
He must use such straightforward language
他一定要用這麼直白的語言
come and translate his bible
來去翻譯他的聖經
did he respond to this
他有沒有對這個
He may have observed classical Chinese in
他可能觀察到的文言文在
comment on the prevailing situation in Chinese society
中國社會通行的這種狀況做出評論
this first
這第一個
then again that is to say
那再來就是說
Did he see some
他是不是有見到哪一些
Chinese vernacular
當年的中國的白話
vernacular-like text
類似白話的文本
pretty passable
還蠻通行
Quite able to call people
還蠻能夠所謂叫人
That's why he translated his bible like this
所以他才這樣子來翻譯他的聖經
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you
謝謝你
this is a very good question
這是一個非常好的問題
let me this take me just this
讓我這個把我剛剛這個
In fact, what should be said is
其實應該講的是
guest in this world
客於這個世界
I really can't speak
我實在是沒辦法講
In fact, we have always had an idea
其實我們一直有一個觀念
thought that this jesus would
以為說這個耶穌會
came to China
是來到中國這個
Only learning this classical Chinese can lead to upward development
只學這個文言文是往上發展的
That is to say
也就是說
In the past, the development of the husband class was preached
往世代夫階級這個發展傳教去的
OK
OK
That
那
it's a big one
這是一個很大的一個
at least in percent of this
至少在百分之這個
forty to fifty percent above
百分之四十到五十上面
This is a mistake
這是一個錯誤
OK
OK
The Jesuits certainly wrote a lot of literary books
耶穌會固然是寫了很多文文文的書
But throughout the Jesuit tradition
可是耶穌會的整個傳統裡面
There are also many books written in vernacular
白話文寫的書也不少
also a lot
也不少
And there are many of these books
而且這些書有很多
Because of the understanding of the Chinese
因為經過中國人的認識
It's actually beautifully written
其實寫得還真是漂亮
Vernacular Novels of the Ming and Qing Dynasties
跟明清兩代的白話小說
is avoidable
是可以避免的
I think He Jinnai
我覺得賀金奈
The first one, of course he was influenced by luck
第一個當然他受到神就運的影響
The second one I can't quite agree with.
第二個其實我沒有辦法完全同意
What you just said was in the pre-Canadian era
你剛剛說的在前加時代
Classical Chinese seems to be a dominant language
文言人好像是一個dominant的語言
a bully language
一種霸君語言
what i was actually trying to say was
我其實正想說的是
I think that in the general middle and lower society of the pre-Canadian era
我覺得在前加時代的一般中下社會裡面
The real language of power is vernacular
真正的權力語言是白話文
OK is vernacular
OK是白話文
I can't only
我不是只能
I don't mean this vernacular novel
我不是指這個白話小說
this kind of popular fiction and stuff like that
這類的通俗小說這一類的東西
I mean, let's say
我指的是,比方說吧
The Victory News
這個勝利廣訊
OK, Shengli Guangxun
OK,勝利廣訊
Well, Shengli Guangxun, to be honest, this
那勝利廣訊說實在的這個
The original, the original thing
原來的,原來的這個東西啊
If you haven't passed by Wang Youpu
如果沒有經過王又普啊
Wang Youpu is a disciple of this Fangbao
王又普是這個方包的弟子
OK, without Wang Youpu
OK,沒有經過王又普這一個把
He rewrote it into vernacular
他改寫成了白話文
OK, there is another person
OK,還有另外一個人
There are two very popular books in total
總共有兩本非常非常popular的這個
This one of Shengli Guangxun, they are called Guangxun Xie
勝利廣訊的這個,他們叫廣訊解啦
explain it, ok
解釋啦,OK
It's all vernacular, OK
其實都是白話文,OK
The vernacular writing is also really good, OK
那個白話文寫的也真是棒,OK
Without these, without these two vernacular texts
沒有這些,沒有這兩本這個白話文
That's especially Guangxunjie
那尤其是廣訊解
It's Wang Youpu's book, OK
就是王又普那一本書啊,OK
I doubt this victory
我懷疑這個勝利廣訊
this victory, ok
這個勝利啊,OK
this victory, he
這個勝利,他
To what extent can it penetrate into the hearts of the people?
能夠深入人心到什麼樣子的程度
The in-depth broadcast is
那個深入廣訊是
Make this Morison very
讓這個Morison非常
Influence Morison
影響Morison
deeply affected
影響得非常深
Morison would love to say
Morison很想說
I will use this text from Guangxun to translate
我就用深入廣訊的這個文字來翻譯吧
OK
OK
just it later this
只是它後來這個
it came after this
它後來這個
Superstitious about this one again
又迷信起這一個說
have to use
非得用
not document
不是文件文
That means
那就是說
Thai is not good either
泰文也不好
Taibai is not good either
泰白也不好
So it ends up taking
所以它最後採
subtext
這種所謂的潛文理
OK
OK
this subject matter
這種題材
Let's translate this sacred book
來翻譯這個神天聖書
The subtext is written in the handwriting of foreigners
那潛文理在外國人的手文裡寫起來
In fact, there will be no white
其實是不會有白的
The kind of taste that the good country interprets
那個善國演繹的那種味道的
OK
OK
so
所以
The sacred book becomes one
神天聖書就變成是一本
it's a mouthful to read
讀起來很拗口的
one book
一本書
OK
OK
I actually think this
我其實我認為這個
Well
呃
rely on that
靠那
He was affected by this dream of Jiu Zun
他受到九尊的這個夢的影響
In fact, the success of Wang Yepu's Guangxun Festival
其實王業浦這個廣訊節的成功
Also one, although he didn't make it clear
也是一個雖然他沒有明白說的一個
At least it was the prevailing social situation at that time
至少是當時社會流行的這個狀況
he sees clearly
他看得很清楚
because he can't follow
因為他不能跟
because going to politics he
因為前往政治他
socialize with the upper class
跟上層人物交往
OK
OK
you can't date seven years
你不能跟七年交往
you can't associate with nobles
你不能跟貴族交往
you want to date
你要交往
Then go to even give him this one special one fate
然後前往甚至給他遇到這一個特別的一個命運
scheduled to say
預定說
You don't preach to the one above
你不要往上面這一個傳教
OK
OK
You have to explain this Catholic truth to this world-class man
你要跟這個世經小民講講這一個天主教的道理
nothing too big a problem with this
沒有什麼太大的這個問題
OK
OK
i want these
我想這些
Of course it all contributed to why he
當然都是促成為什麼他
in an era of pre-dragons
在前龍的一個時代
He decided to use this vernacular
他決定用這一個白話文
to translate
來翻譯
OK
OK
Then I'll look at dating as a whole
那我就約會整體來看
Probably this era of Limadou
大概立馬豆的這個時代
Limadou itself already uses the vernacular
立馬豆本身就已經用白話
preaching to this lower class
在對這個下層傳教了
This is his more
這是他比較多的
More time is spent with the upper layer
更多的時間是跟上層這個在一起
So he also wrote that Catechism
所以他也寫了那個Catechism
Q&A on transactions
就交易問答
he wrote in vernacular
他是用白話文寫的
Then you probably from this
那你從這個大概
That's about 1605 or so.
那差不多是1605年左右的這個事情
that book was engraved
那書是有刻出來的
you can look all the way down
你可以一路看下來
Seeing He Qingdai's era
看到賀青代這一個時代
that jesus book written in vernacular
那個耶穌會用白話文寫的書
There are more than fifty or sixty kinds
五六十種以上都有
OK
OK
If you want to search harder
你如果要再好好的找的話
Maybe there are more than fifty or sixty kinds
搞不好不只五六十種
OK
OK
i say the whole thing
我整個都說
He Qingdai is the fifty or sixty kinds
賀青代是這五六十種
Or perhaps not only the fifty
或者說可能不只這五十
some things we just can't see
有些東西我們實在是看不到
OK
OK
not yet visible
目前還看不到
He wrote in these vernacular
他是這一些白話文寫
top performer
面的極大成者
he wrote the most
他寫的最多
most intentional
他意的最多
And what?
而且呢
very very
非常非常
Interestingly
有趣的是
This he is not like this traditional novel
這個他不像這個傳統小說一樣
ok
ok
What about traditional novels?
傳統小說呢
vernacular novels have their fixed
白話小說有他固定的
rhythm of speech
講話的節奏
ok
ok
this rhythm of writing
行文的這個節奏
He Jinnai doesn't have this set at all
何金奈完全沒有這一套
the way he speaks
他講話的方式呢
he writes articles
他寫文章
sorry for the way this bible was translated
對不起翻譯這個聖經的方式
like the way we write today
就像我們今天寫作的這個樣子一樣的
We are actually speaking here today including me
我們今天其實包括我在這裡講話
In fact, we all use the European topic
其實我們都用的是歐話題
speaking
在講話的
ok
ok
us
我們
not with the traditional
不是用傳統這個
Well
呃
Let's say this one
比方說這個一個
The language in Western Europe
西歐記裡面的這個語言
Or the language in Hongaomeng
或者說紅澳夢裡面的這個語言
speaking
在講話的
ok
ok
that language instant
那種語言即使
There is no way in the true biography
真文傳裡面都沒辦法
ok
ok
This article we
這文章我們
Because there's going to be a rush to act
因為會出現那種趕快採取行動
OK
OK
Hello, thanks
你好 謝謝
Thank you for the most extraordinary speech
謝謝您最不一樣精彩的演講
I actually have a question
我其實有個疑問
that is
就是說
You said He Qingtai's vernacular nerves
你說賀清泰的這個白話文的神經
In fact, it affects the later
其實影響到後來的
That version of Loberto Morrison's
馬里遜的Lobberto Morrison的那個版本
to my limited knowledge
據我有限的知識
I know Lobberto Morrison
我知道Lobberto Morrison
When he started to prevent the epidemic
當他開始在防疫的時候
he went to london
他去了倫敦
Went to the British Museum
去了British Museum裡面
copied one
抄了一個
I don't know where it came from a nerve
不知道是哪裡來的一個神經
Then take him as the first book
然後是以他為第一本
Then I met another person in Guangzhou
然後又在廣州遇到的一個人
A nerve gifted to him
人家送給他的一個神經
that's what you said
那個就是您所說的
It may be the version of He Qingtai mentioned
可能是所說的賀清泰的這個版本
But they are generally
但是它們總體上來說
It is still mainly in accordance with the
它還是主要是依照那個
The version in the British Museum
British Museum裡面的那個版本的
I think
我想
I'd like to hear more from you about the ins and outs of this
我想聽你多講一下有關這一方面的來龍去脈
Thanks
謝謝
I certainly thought this one was supposed to be adapted to the right
我當然也以為這一個應該是適應右邊
The impact on Doctor Cat should be a bit heavier
對於貓醫生的這個影響應該會比較重一點
because history says so
因為歷史上都是這麼說的
That's what many people say
很多人都是這麼說的
But when the text on the right
可是適時右邊的這個文字
There is no editor like this horse medical news
還沒有這個馬醫訊那樣子的這一個編輯
you are so editing my words
你這麼要編輯我的話
That's He Jintai
那是賀金太
He Jintai, he wants to Wen Baijiazai
賀金太這個他要溫白家雜
He can't have a gentle relationship
他沒有辦法溫白交往
ok
ok
He was also very uncouth when he was gentle with Bai’s family. This Chinese
他溫白家雜的時候那也是很不勇的這一個中文
Not like vernacular, not like Wenyuan
不像白話不像文元
ok
ok
That's how Doctor Cat is translating
那貓醫生就是這樣在翻譯的
Well
呃
this so
這個所以
I certainly can't say that this is a cat doctor
我當然不能夠說這一個貓醫生
Didn't receive this impact on the right side of this one
沒有收過這一個適時右邊的這個影響
I'm afraid that Dr. Cat's influence on the right side is quite big.
恐怕貓醫生適時右邊的影響還蠻大的
ok
ok
But what?
可是呢
He Jintai's stock gold body is also standing in front of Dr. Cat
賀金太的股金身體也賀然立在貓醫生
Because when Doctor Cat translated the Bible himself
因為貓醫生自己翻譯聖經的時候
He himself listed several of his reference books
他自己列了幾本他的參考書
The "Old and New Bible" is in this grade
《古新聖經》就在這檔次檔次檔中
OK
OK
so i dare not say this one
所以我不敢說這一個
His influence
他影響力
The influence of the ancient and new bibles is so great that this one is bigger than the forty-one and two sides
古新聖經影響力大到這一個比四十一二邊還要大
But it has an effect on the cat doctor
但是對貓醫生是有影響的
At least my research so far
至少我的研究到目前為止
as far as i know
我所知道大概是這樣子
Let's compare their writing styles
我們好好去比對他們的文風
Perhaps it can be seen that Doctor Cat is more
或許可以看出貓醫生是比較
The 412 side of Pro is still more inclined
Pro的四十一二邊還是比較傾向
the old new bible
這個古新聖經
OK
OK
that takes a lot of time
那需要很多時間就是了
OK thank you
OK 謝謝
I think we are very thankful for this Christmas today
我想我們今天非常感謝這個聖誕節
I heard Li Sixue called
聽到李嗣學叫做
It turned into He Qingtai
演然變成賀清泰了
Made a very in-depth and wonderful program
做了非常深入非常精彩的節目
thank you
謝謝各位